<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian warning-piece for all true Protestants by way of Christian counsel and advice to the King's most excellent Majesty, and all his good Protestant subjects, founded forth out of the written word of God : wherein is clearly shewed ... / by Thomas Wall.</title>
            <author>Wall, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67317</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W476</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34705</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14573912</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14573912</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102616</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67317)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102616)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1079:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian warning-piece for all true Protestants by way of Christian counsel and advice to the King's most excellent Majesty, and all his good Protestant subjects, founded forth out of the written word of God : wherein is clearly shewed ... / by Thomas Wall.</title>
                  <author>Wall, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102616:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHRISTIAN WARNING-PIECE FOR ALL TRUE PROTESTANTS BY WAY OF CHRISTIAN COUNSEL and ADVICE TO THE KING'S Moſt Excellent MAJESTY, and all His good Proteſtant Subjects, ſounded forth out of the Written Word of GOD.</p>
            <p>Wherein is clearly ſhewed, the true Cauſes why the Lord in former Ages brought his ſevere Judgments on his own People, both before the Law, under the Law, and under the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>All which being applied to the preſent State of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> is proved both by Scripture and Hiſtory, that it is the ſame Cauſe ſtill for which the Lord is bringing His ſevere Judgments on his Proteſtant People: Toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Means, if imbraced, which God in Mercy hath Ordained to prevent the ſame.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> WALL.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Cry aloud, ſpare not, lift up thy Voice like a Trumpet, and ſhew my People their Tranſgreſſions, and the Houſe of</hi> Jacob <hi>their Sins.</hi> 
               <bibl>Iſa. 58. 1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>For whatſoever things were written aforetime, were written for our Learning, and Admonition, upon whom the ends of the World are come. Therefore let him that thinketh he ſtandeth, take heed leſt he fall.</hi> 
               <bibl>Rom. 15. 4. 1 Cor. 10. 11.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Whoſoever heareth the ſound of the Trumpet, and taketh not Warning, his Blood ſhall be upon his own Head: But he that taketh Warning, ſhall deliver his own Soul.</hi> 
               <bibl>Ezek. 33. 4, 5.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:102616:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102616:2"/>
            <head>TO THE King's Moſt Excellent Majeſty.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt humbly ſhewing,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>THat the moſt Wiſe God, who hath made all things for his</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 4. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Pleaſure, hath ordained in every Nation but two States, Pillers, or Legs, to ſtand upon; the one Civil, and the other Spiritual. The Civil State is God's Ordinance of Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Government, under divers Titles, as Kings, or other Chief Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, unto whom an excellent</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Dan. 4. 36.</note> 
               <hi>Majeſty is given them of God, as next under</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> 
               <hi>God, Head of the Commonwealth, the Lord's Lieutenants here on Earth. And ſeeing ſince the Fall, Mans Heart is</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 17. 9.</note> 
               <hi>deceitful, and in Mans Fleſh dwelleth no good thing, ſo that</hi> the Good he would do, he doth not; but the Evil he would not, that he doth <note n="†" place="margin">Rom. 7.</note>. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for guide in Government, God hath given Kings the ſecond</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Table of his Royal Law, as a moſt ſure Foundation and Rule, to ſquare all their Laws by to govern their People; ſo that by it they bear not the Sword in vain, but uſe it to the Glory of God, for the puniſhment of Evil-doers</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 13.</note>, <hi>and the praiſe of them that do well: Of which Truſt and Stewardſhip committed to them, they muſt ſhortly give an Account to their Chief Judg, the Prince of the Kings of the Earth, the Lord Jeſus, at the laſt Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The other State or Piller is the</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 15. 3 <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 18</note> 
               <hi>Kingly Government of the Lord Jeſus in his Church, or</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">John 18. 36.</note> 
               <hi>Kingdom, in all things Spiritual. As Chriſt hath his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice under God, the only Head of his Myſtical Body</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 23. Col. 1. 17.</note> 
               <hi>the Church, unto whoſe Government is given the firſt Table of God's Law, according to which moſt ſure Foundation are all the Laws made in all Ages for his worſhip: And though Chriſt was not manifeſted in the Fleſh till theſe laſt Times, yet was he from the Days of</hi> Adam <hi>King in his Church, on his holy</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Pſal. 2. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Hill of</hi> Sion, <hi>in thoſe who were Figures of him, as</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 7. 1. Pſ. 110. 4.</note> Melchiſedeck, <note n="‖" place="margin">Acts 3. 22.</note> Moſes, <hi>and</hi> David; <hi>ſo Chriſt was the ſame Yeſterday, to Day, and for</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Heb. 13. 8</note> 
               <hi>ever, who now in his Church ſitteth on the Throne of his Father</hi> David, <hi>as it is written of him,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 11. 3, 4.</note> That he ſhall not judg after the ſight of his Eyes, nor reprove after the hearing of his Ears; but with Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſhall he judg the Poor, and reprove with Equity, for the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102616:3"/> Meek of the Earth: and ſhall ſmite the Earth with the Rod of his Mouth, and with the breath of his Lips ſhall he ſlay the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>So that his Weapons are not Carnal, as his Kingdom is not of this World; ſo differing from the Civil State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moreover, as theſe be the only States ordained of God, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of them being ſo different the one from the other, as the nature of a thing Civil and Spiritual is, ſo that the one State may not meddle with the Work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that belongeth to the other. And hereupon did the Lord in his Wiſdom, conſtitute the Civil State in the Tribe of</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 49. 10. 2 Chron. 5. 2.</note> Judah, <hi>and the Spiritual State in the Tribe of</hi> Levi; <hi>but when King</hi> Uzziah <hi>would preſume to break God's Order, to do that Work which</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">2 Chron. 27. 16, 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>belonged not to the Civil States Office, the Lord ſmote him with Leproſie to the day of his Death; that others may be warned, not to preſume above what is written,</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore the Lord Jeſus, our High Prieſt, and only Lord Spiritual in his Church, would not meddle with the Magiſtrates-work nor Office, to give Judgment on a Woman taken in Adultery</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">John 8. 3, 4, 5.</note>, <hi>nor divide Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances between Brethren: And likewiſe commanded his Diſciples, and all Biſhops and Miniſters to the Worlds end, not to take on them the title</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 22. 25. Mat. 20. 25.</note> 
               <hi>of Politick Princes, but rather he that would be Chief, to be Servant to all; and not as Lords, either in Title or Rule, over God's Heritage</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 3.</note>, <hi>or Churches of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore we ſee God in his Wiſdom hath limited either State to keep within the limits he hath ordained for them. Therefore as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Civil Magiſtratical State, we may juſtly conclude, That whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Perſon he be, whether Noble or Ignoble, that ſhall preſume to Alter, Change, or Diminiſh to, or from any part of the Laws, Ordinances, Offices, or Order, contrary to the King's Royal Crown and Dignity eſtabliſhed by Law, according to the ſecond Table of God's Law, muſt needs be accounted a Traytor to the King, and ſuffer his high Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accordingly may we conclude, concerning the Spiritual State of Chriſt's Government in his Church, That whatſoever Perſon he be, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Noble, or Ignoble, that ſhall preſume to Add or Diminiſh, Alter or Change any thing in Government, or Miniſtry, Time, Maintenance or Order, contrary to the Rules or Laws of Chriſt's Teſtament, founded on the firſt Table of God's Law, in all things pertaining to the Worſhip of God, may juſtly be deemed a Traytor to the Royal Crown and Dignity of the Lord Jeſus; and may hear the Sentence out of his own Mouth againſt them, ſaying,</hi> Bring thoſe mine Enemies that would not that I ſhould Reign over them, and ſlay them before me: <hi>Either</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102616:3"/> 
               <hi>by caſting out of his Church, or by everlaſting Wo at the laſt Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>May it therefore pleaſe your Majeſty, in your Wiſdom to conſider theſe things, That it is one of the Crying Sins in this your Kingdom, for which God's Judgments are threatned againſt it, becauſe the Civil and Spiritual State is mingled together; the Civil State aſſuming into the Spiritual Prerogative of the Lord Jeſus (who hath this Teſtimony from God, that he was faithful in his Houſe, or Church, as</hi> Moſes, <hi>to give Laws and Directions in every thing appertaining to the Worſhip of God) to make Laws and Directions how, and what we muſt worſhip God with and by. The Miniſters, or Biſhops, contrary to Chriſt's expreſs Word and Practice, do take on them the Office of Civil State, and Titles of Politick Princes, to be Lords in Councils, as Parliaments, and Lords Spiritual in and over Churches, if not Juſtices of the Peace; ſo that by this breach of God's Order, there is ſuch a ſtate of Confuſion; to wit, A third State, or Leg, a Compound of both Civil and Spiritual, yet neither really Civil nor Spiritual; but a Monſter, called a Beaſt,</hi> Rev. 13. 1, 11. <hi>Which, as Writers ſay</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Plat. Politiq. See <hi>Hen. Ainſ. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>was firſt brought forth in</hi> Egypt, <hi>by thoſe Heathens void of God's Order in Grace and Nature, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would have all their Kings, Prieſts; ſo commingling the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Prieſthood together in one Perſon. And this abominable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention was the</hi> Romiſh <hi>Church, when fallen from Chriſt, enamoured with; for which ſinful Act, among others, ſhe is called not only</hi> Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon <note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 18. &amp; Rev. 11.</note>, Sodom, <hi>but</hi> Egypt, <hi>becauſe the</hi> Romiſh <hi>Church would have the Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, Princedom and Prieſthood, in the perſons of her Popes, Cardinals, and Biſhops, to be Church Princes, and indeed above Princes, to Dethrone them at their pleaſure; and from</hi> Rome <hi>was this</hi> Egyptian <hi>Faſhion brought by her</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 18. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Merchants into</hi> England. <hi>And this being ſuch a Confuſion, that the very</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Pont. l. 5. c. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Philoſopher condemneth it by the light of Nature, and ſays, it could not ſtand with the actions of thoſe two Offices (meaning the Civil and Spiritual) ſo different the one from the other, that one Man ſhould perform both at one time toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but muſt needs fall out, when both Duties are to be done, that the one would be omitted. So either God is not duly ſerved, or the Civil State ſuffers Damage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And for as much as it is a work belonging to the Civil State to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, which your Majeſties Anceſtors, King</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> 8th, <hi>King</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>the</hi> 6th, <hi>and Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>of happy Memory, began (as God had promiſed, That he would put into the Hearts of the Kings of the Earth, to hate the Whore, eat her Fleſh, and</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 17. 16.</note> 
               <hi>burn her by the Fiery Law of God, in making her deſolate and naked) to aboliſh out of their Dominions the Pope's Supremacy, the Lord Abbots, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102616:4"/> Jeſuits, Monks, Friers; and the reſt of that Miniſtry is left for your Majeſty to aboliſh; which if your Majeſty refuſe to do, it muſt be done: And why? Becauſe the Lord hath ſaid it; who will (by whom he pleaſes) give them Blood to drink, for ſtrong is the Lord that judgeth her. And the Kings of the Earth, who have committed Fornication, and lived deliciouſly with her, yet now ſhall bewail her, and lament for her, when they ſhall ſee the ſmoke of her Burning; as more at large is written,</hi> Rev. 18. 8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>And all Magiſtrates that endeavour to hinder it, are withſtanders of God's Word; becauſe in her is found the Blood of the Prophets, and of the Saints, and of all that were ſlain upon the Earth</hi> (Oh Bloody Papiſts!) <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And hereupon it is written, Rev.</hi> 17. 6. I ſaw the Woman drunken with the Blood of Saints, and with the Blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus. <hi>Which Woman, is clearly in this enſuing Book, proved to be the Church of</hi> Rome; For every Tree is known by its Fruit <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 7. 20.</note>. <hi>Therefore the chiefeſt Article of her Faith, is to Murder all that believe not as She believeth. Now ſo far is that Church from being the Church of Chriſt, or Children of God; that they are Children of the Devil</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">John 8.</note>, <hi>who was a Murderer from the beginning, ſo have him (and not God) for their Father; becauſe they do his works to the uttermoſt of their power. Witneſs their Cruelty in Queen</hi> Marie's <hi>days, the</hi> Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Plot, <hi>and now this</hi> Helliſh Plot <hi>to take away the Life of your Majeſty, and your good Proteſtant Subjects: As they began with that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Knight, Sir</hi> Edmondbury Godfrey; <hi>and will never be out of hopes of coming to poſſeſs this Land, whilſt Proteſtants can imbrace their Brethren in Office of Arch and Lord-Biſhops, Arch-Deacons, Deans, Prebends; which Offices for Goſpel-Miniſters, Chriſt's Teſtament knows nothing of, but the Pope's Records. Oh therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Lord would be pleaſed to open your Majeſties Heart, to Act as a moſt Worthy Proteſtant Prince, as with the</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 14. 22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>Beeſom of the Lord, to ſweep out of your Dominions (not ſo much in their Perſons, as out of Office) the remaining part of the</hi> Romiſh <hi>Miniſtry, by Law of overſight eſtabliſhed in Proteſtant Churches, together with all other Popiſh De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices in Worſhip; ſome of many are after noted. And for your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties glorious Preſident in this ſo excellent a Work, for the Honour of God and good of his People, who as Proteſtants will live and die with You; Caſt your Majeſtie's Eye on that young King</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">2 Chron. 34</note> Joſiah, <hi>who ſo ſoon as he heard of the Judgments of God denounced againſt his Land and People, called for, the Book of the Law to be read before him, and by it comparing the Acts of his Fore-Fathers, and preſent ſtate of his Kingdom, rent his Clothes; And for fear of the Judgments of God, in the</hi> 16th
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102616:4"/> 
               <hi>Year of his Age, and</hi> 8th <hi>Year of his Reign, began to ſeek the Lord, and in the</hi> 12th <hi>Year began to purge out of his Dominions the Reliques of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, all Devices of Men in Worſhip, ſet up by former Kings, together with the falſe Miniſtry, called</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Zeph 1. 4</note> Chemarims, <hi>either for their Black Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they wore, or being ſmoked in offering Incenſe to Idols; (as the Margent of the great Bible noteth) and reſtored the Lord's true Miniſtry and holy order of Worſhip, as the Lord had appointed by the hand of</hi> Moſes. <hi>Which if your Majeſty will do this like Glorious Work by the Light of Chriſt's Teſtament, comparing the Acts of your Predeceſſors, and preſent ſtate of your Kingdom, ſo poluted with a</hi> Romiſh <hi>Miniſtry, and other Inventions in Proteſtant Churches, that ſo a true Miniſtry, according to the Lord's Will in Chriſt's Teſtiment, may be enjoyed, and the People left free to chooſe their own Miniſters (according to Nature and Grace) to grow out of every particular</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Can. 8. 8. Ezek. 16. 7. Acts 14. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Body, or Congregation, and not by Humane Art for Miniſters to be made by they know not whom, and ſet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the Body whether they will or no, as an artificial Eye or Breſt. So ſhall your Majeſty and People hope, as King</hi> Joſiah <hi>and his People did, that the Judgments threatned againſt this Land may be turned away, as it was from his. As it is proved in the following Lines, that it was chiefly for corruptions in Faith and Worſhip, that God brought his Judgments on his own People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now, would it pleaſe your Majeſty in your Civil Kingdom to ſuffer your Self to be ſo abuſed, as to have no Servants to ſerve You in your Kingdom, or at your Table, but what the King of another Nation think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth fit? No ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How then ſhall the Lord Jeſus, the Prince of the Kings of the Earth, ſuffer himſelf any longer to be ſo Abuſed, as to have no Servants to ſerve Him in his Church of his own Appointment, either in Name or Office, as Paſtors Teachers, Elders, and Deacons, but what the Pope, or other Mortal Men think fit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neither would your Majeſty accept of the Service of any Subject, Noble or Ignoble, that ſhould proffer his Service to ſerve You in your Civil Affairs, if he did not do the ſame as your Majeſty had given him Command, and not as he pleaſed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How then ſhall the Lord Jeſus accept, nay, he doth not accept of the Service of any Perſon, of what Degree ſoever, that ſhall in his Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Kingdom, or Church, ſerve him never ſo zealouſly, except he do that Work and Service to God, as Chriſt in his Teſtament hath commanded him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If it were not ſo, the very</hi> Turks <hi>that boaſt how they are Worſhippers of the Living God, and do abhor Idols, would go beyond many that bear</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:102616:5"/> 
               <hi>the name of Chriſtians; who though they do zealouſly worſhip the Living</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Beal.</hi> Ep. to image of both Churches.</note> 
               <hi>God, and concerning Chriſt, allow him to be a great Prophet, the Word of God, the Spirit of God, born of</hi> Mary <hi>the Virgin; yet becauſe they worſhip not God by the Appointment of the Lord Jeſus in his Teſtament, but according to the directions of</hi> Mahomet, <hi>therefore are they and their ſervices rejected of God. So likewiſe, the</hi> Papiſts <hi>boaſt how they worſhip God, (yet abhor not Idols) but becauſe they do it by direction of ſundry Popes, and not by Chriſt's Appointment, they are rejected of God and their ſervice. But if a</hi> Turk <hi>or</hi> Papiſt <hi>ſhould ask many</hi> Proteſtants, <hi>By whoſe Appointments do you worſhip God? If truly anſwered, muſt ſay, Partly by the directions of Chriſt, (for we have his Ordinances of Baptiſm, and the Lord's Supper) and partly by the Appointments of ſundry Popes and Biſhops, as after is ſhewed. So that for theſe things, among other Evils, God is bringing his Judgments on your Kingdom. Oh therefore, that your Majeſty, together with your Honorable Council, would ſeriouſly conſider theſe things, that the Wrath of the Lord may be turned away from us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And laſtly, Seeing there is but one way to eſcape God's Judgments threatned, let not a Heathen Prince (as Chriſt told the</hi> Jews) <hi>come in Judgment at the laſt Day againſt a Chriſtian Prince,</hi> viz. <hi>the King of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jonah 3.</note> Nineveh, <hi>who ſo ſoon as he heard the Judgment of God threatned againſt him and his People, aroſe from his Throne and laid his Robes from him, iſſued forth a Proclamation to his People, to keep a true Faſt to the Lord as he required; that is, to break off their Sins by Repentance, in turning every one from his evil way, and from the violence that was in their Hands, who did ſo; ſo that it is written,</hi> God ſaw their Works, and repented of the evil he threatned againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus having diſcharged the part of a true Proteſtant Subject, preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a Wiſe Proteſtant Prince, not doubting but this Mite ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted and protected by yonr Majeſty in Chriſtian love to the Truth, for the Honour of God, and comfort of your Soul, and the joy and comfort of your Proteſtant Subjects: So that your Majeſty (with the Godly Kings of</hi> Judah) <hi>doing the Will of God herein, may have many Years</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 13. 36. Rev. 21. 24.</note> 
               <hi>on Earth a proſperous Reign; and having brought your Honour and Glory to the glorious State of Chriſt's Kingdom in his Church, whereby She may enjoy all her Rights and Priviledges, you may undoubtedly receive with Chriſt a Crown of Glory eternally in the Heavens; which is and ſhall be, the Prayer of your moſt humble Subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO. WALL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:102616:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Word of Advice to all true Proteſtants.</head>
            <p>AS it is the duty of every true Chriſtian not to hide his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant in the <note n="*" place="margin">Luke. 19. with Mark 25. 25.</note> Earth, but put it on a Candleſtick, that all may be benefited by the ſame; I therefore judg, if ever there were a time to ſpeak, it is now, when the Proteſtant Religion lieth at ſtake to be utterly Ruined, and the Profeſſors thereof Murdered by the Blood-thirſty Papiſts, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> the Rod of God's Anger <note n="†" place="margin">Iſa. 10. 5.</note> againſt his own People: So that as Affliction doth not come out of the <note n="‖" place="margin">Job 5. 6.</note> Duſt, nor Trouble ſpring out of the Ground; for (as ſaith the Scripture) <hi>Is there any Evil</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Amos 3. 6.</note> 
               <hi>in the City,</hi> (to wit, of Puniſhment) <hi>and I have not done it, ſaith the Lord?</hi> And, when the Lord giveth <hi>Quietneſs, who can make</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Job 34. 29.</note> 
               <hi>Trouble? and when he hideth his Face, who can behold him? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be done againſt a Nation, or a Man only.</hi> Therefore I have thought it the moſt profitable way, to ſhew what I have gathered out of holy Scripture, was the cauſe in Ages paſt that the Lord brought Judgments on his own People, and to apply the ſame to our preſent Condition: Which if the Lord help us truly to mind the ſame, as Chriſtians ought to do, it may be a means to obtain Mercy at the Hand of the Lord, to turn away his Judgments. Let us take a view of theſe things from the firſt State of old.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> When God had graciouſly reſtored <hi>Adam,</hi> by his Grace in Chriſt promiſed, and given him Ordinances as Figures of Chriſt to come, to perform in the Lord's holy order of Worſhip, which in the days of his Son <hi>Enos,</hi> his Children had greatly departed from, corrupted their Way, meaning their <note n="‖" place="margin">Gen. 6. 12. with Acts 18. 25. and 22. 4.</note> Faith and Religion, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo their making Marriages with <hi>Cain</hi>'s Poſterity, called <hi>the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Men,</hi> which was not lawful for the Members of the Church, called the <hi>Sons of God,</hi> to do; and though God called them to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance by <hi>Noah</hi>'s Preaching, and warned them, by his building the Ark, of the Judgment intended by the Flood; yet they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in their evil Courſe, untill the Flood deſtroyed them all:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102616:6"/> And how like to this, is the ſtate of Luke-warm Proteſtants now? So that Chriſt likened the laſt Days we are fallen in, to the Days of <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 17. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Noah,</hi> for Sin and Wickedneſs, by departing from the true Faith, and by corruption in Worſhip, and Members of Churches now making Marriages with thoſe they cannot in Conſcience joyn with in the Ordinances of Worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Though God did miraculouſly ſave Eight Souls by <note n="†" place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 20.</note> Water, yet in the days of <hi>Ferah,</hi> the Father of <hi>Abraham,</hi> was the Church ſo corrupted in Faith and Worſhip, that God forſook them, and called <hi>Abraham</hi> thence <note n="‖" place="margin">Gen. 11. 12. Joſh. 24. 2.</note> and they that would go with him; ſo God made his Covenant in Chriſt with him and his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, which went in proceſs of time into <hi>Egypt.</hi> But when they defiled themſelves with the <note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. 20. 7.</note> Idols of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and were corrupted in their Faith and Worſhip, the Lord made the King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the Rod of his Anger <note n="†" place="margin">Exod. 2. 23.</note>, grievouſly to Afflict them: How like is this to the Condition of Corrupt Proteſtants now in their Faith and Worſhip?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Lord, for his own Name ſake, firſt by his Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and then by his Promiſes and Wonders <note n="‖" place="margin">Exod. 4. 30.</note>, won them again to his true Faith and Worſhip; and then he quickly deſtroyed their Oppreſſors in the Sea, and afterwards in the Wilderneſs gave them his juſt Precepts between Man and Man, and his holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and Decrees for Worſhip, which when they broke, the Lord <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 10. Numb. 16. 31.</note> deſtroyed, ſome by the Sword of their Enemies, and others by the Sword of their own Brethren: Some the Earth open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſwallowed up alive, others died of the Peſtilence; ſo that within the ſpace of forty Years, of 600000 Fighting Men that came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but two <note n="†" place="margin">Numb. 14. 24. 2 Cor. 10.</note> entred <hi>Canaan:</hi> And <hi>this is written,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>for enſample</hi> to us Proteſtants, <hi>on whom the Ends of the World are come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> When God by the hand of <hi>Joſhua</hi> brought their Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity into <hi>Canaan,</hi> the Lord ſtrictly charged them concerning their Faith and Worſhip, ſaying, <hi>After the</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Lev. 18. 2, 3,</note> 
               <hi>doings of the Land of</hi> Egypt <hi>wherein ye dwelt, ye ſhall not do: neither after the doings of the Land of</hi> Canaan <hi>whither I bring you, ſhall ye not do, neither walk in their Ordinances: My Judgments ſhall ye do, my Ordinances ſhall ye keep to walk in them, I am the Lord.</hi> Yea, they were not ſo much as to <note n="†" place="margin">Deut. 12. 32.</note> enquire how the Nations ſerved their Gods, that they might do ſo unto the Lord their God; but whatſoever the Lord commanded them, they ſhould take heed to do, without adding or diminiſhing. But how quickly after the death of <hi>Joſhua,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102616:6"/> and the Elders of his Time, did they corrupt themſelves with the Inventions of Men in their Worſhip, for which the Lord ſold them into their Enemies hands <note n="*" place="margin">Judges ch. 2.</note>, that ſo they could no longer ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. And will not Proteſtants mind this in our day of Danger?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> And was not King <hi>Solomon</hi> beloved of his God, who appeared to him twice? Yet when he was drawn away with his Idolatrous and ſtraying Wives to a Worſhip deviſed by Man, did not God ſtir up Adverſaries <note n="†" place="margin">2 Kings 11. 14, 25.</note> againſt him, <hi>Hadad</hi> the <hi>Edomite,</hi> and <hi>Rezon,</hi> who were Adverſaries to <hi>Solomon</hi> all his days? And ſhall not Kings remember this? Becauſe the Judge of all the Earth will reward every one according to their Works. And when <hi>Rehoboam, Solomon</hi>'s Son, who was brought up in the Ways of the Lord, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook, the ſame, the Lord ſtirred up <hi>Shiſhack</hi> King <note n="‖" place="margin">2 Chron. 12. 12. 1 Kings 14. 24.</note> of <hi>Egypt</hi> to come againſt him to his great Prejudice. And when the ten Tribes under King <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> worſhipped God by the <note n="*" place="margin">2 Chron. 11. 15.</note> devices of Men, and by another Miniſtry than what God had ordained, they were not only ſaid to be without the True God, without a Teaching Prieſt, and without Law, but there was no <note n="†" place="margin">2 Chron. 15. 3, 4, 5, 6</note> Peace to him that went out, nor to him that came in; Nation was deſtroyed of Nation, City of City, <hi>for God did vex them,</hi> ſaith the Scripture, <hi>with all Adverſity.</hi> And whilſt God was thus chaſtizing them in Meaſure, he ſent his Prophets to call them to his true Faith and Worſhip, which ſtill they deſpiſing, at length the Lord ſtirred up the Spirit of <hi>Pull</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">1 Chron. 5. 26. 2 Kings 15. 19.</note>, and the Spirit of <hi>Tilgath-Pilneſer,</hi> Kings of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> who carried them away into Captivity, to their utter Ruine. And when <hi>Judah</hi> would not take warning, but fell to falſe Worſhip, and would not be reclaimed by the Lord's Prophets, riſing early <note n="*" place="margin">2 Chron. 36. 15. Jer. 25. 3. &amp; 35. 15.</note> ſent to them, and after many Afflictions on them, the Lord ſent againſt <hi>Judah, Rezin</hi> the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> to their great Prejudice. And again the King of <hi>Egypt</hi> came againſt <hi>Judah,</hi> and condemned the Land <note n="†" place="margin">2 Chron. 36. 3.</note> in a hundred Talents of Silver, and a Talent of Gold, yet they were not bettered; then came the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <note n="‖" place="margin">Ver. 18.</note> away many of them Captive with much Spoil; yet they would not repent and return to the Lord's true Faith and Worſhip, but perſecuted the Lord's Prophets; then the Lord gave them again into the hands of the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who burn'd <note n="*" place="margin">2 Chron. 36. 17, 18, 19, 20.</note> both City and Temple, and carried more of them Captive. Thus we ſee the grand cauſe is ſtill for Corruptions in Faith, and Diſorder in Worſhip, that God brought his Judgments on his People: And will not <hi>Proteſtants</hi> mind this, ſeeing the like Judgments for like
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102616:7"/> Cauſes are at our Doors? as will hereafter appear. Therefore,</p>
            <p>Now let us come to Goſpel-Times, and ſee the Cauſes of God's Judgments that fell on Chriſtians in the Primitive Times of the Goſpel, and compare our Condition with theirs in Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages and Rewards, if it be not the ſame ſtill. So that unleſs there be a ſpeedy Repentance, we can expect to fare no better than they. Thus if the Word ſpoken by Angels was ſtedfaſt, and every Tranſgreſſion received a juſt recompence of Reward, though under the performance but of <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 2. 2.</note> Figurative Ordinances, even the ſmalleſt breach of God's Law; as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza</hi> for touching the Ark, was ſtruck dead <note n="†" place="margin">1 Chron. 13. 10. Numb. 4. 15.</note>. <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> for offering of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, were ſwallowed up alive in the Earth; and King <note n="‖" place="margin">2 Chron. 26. 19.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> ſmote with Leproſie to the day of his Death: And likewiſe <hi>Miri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Numb. 12.</note> and <hi>Gehazi</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">2 King. 5.</note>, were they unpuniſhed? No ſure: How then ſhall we eſcape the Judgments of God, having the Word ſpoken unto us by the Son of God, Creator <note n="‖" place="margin">Col. 1. 16.</note> of Angels? ſealed with his precious Blood <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 13. 20.</note>, delivered and commended unto all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans by his Apoſtles <note n="†" place="margin">Acts. 20. 32.</note>, whereunto may nothing be added or diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note n="‖" place="margin">Rev. 22. 19.</note>, either in Doctrine, Miniſtry, Ordinances, Time, or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, according to fleſhly Wiſdom, without Rebellion and moſt hainous Tranſgreſſion, Sacriledg and Impiety, as againſt the Scepter <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 45. 6.</note> of our Lord Jeſus, bleſſed for ever, his Word being commanded to be purely taught, without corrupting or ſwerving either to the right Hand, or to the left: Which when the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians obſerved not, but neglected their Watch <note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 3. 3.</note>, in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering falſe Doctrine to creep in among them, as in the Church of <hi>Pergamos</hi> reigned the Doctrine of <hi>Balaam</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Rev. 2. 14, 15.</note>, and the <hi>Nicolaitans;</hi> and in <hi>Thyatira,</hi> the Doctrine of <hi>Jezebel</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ver. 20.</note>; <hi>Epheſus</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 2. 4</note> having left her firſt Love; and among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and other Chriſtians, both Men and Women, were they not reproved for walking in a vain Converſation? Whilſt Men wearing long Hair, the <note n="‖" place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 14.</note> ſhame of Nature; their Women likewiſe wearing of Gold, Pearl, <note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 9. 1 Pet. 3. 3.</note> plaited Hair, uncovered, expreſly in plain words forbidden by the Apoſtle, not becoming modeſt Women, profeſſing Godlineſs with good Works. For which Evils and Diſorders, with others, becauſe the Churches puniſhed them not according to God's Order, by caſting the <note n="‖" place="margin">Mat. 17. 18.</note> obſtinate Sinners out of the Churches, the Lord Jeſus threatned to caſt them into a Bed of great Tribulation <note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 2. 22.</note>, under the term of ten Prophetical Days (meaning Years) which ſome have obſerved to come on the Churches in the—Year of Chriſt, in the Reign of <hi>Trajan</hi> the Emperour. So that if God in his juſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102616:7"/> Judgment for the Sins of the ten Tribes, delivered them of old into the Hands of the Kings of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and likewiſe <hi>Judah</hi> into the Hands of the King of <hi>Babylon;</hi> even ſo for like Cauſe did the Lord deliver the Eaſt Churches into the Hands of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and the Weſt Churches into the Hands of the Beaſt, the Pope and his Clergie. Unto which agreeth Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi>'s Teſtimony, in his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the <hi>Holy Wars,</hi> [worth all Proteſtants obſervation, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in this Day of Apoſtacy] in <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 6. in theſe words: <q>But the Sins of the Eaſtern Countries, and chiefly their damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Hereſies, haſtened God's Judgments on them: and in the Weſtern parts, Hereſies, as an Angle, caught ſingle Perſons; which in <hi>Aſia,</hi> like a Draw-Net, took whole Provinces. The ſtaid and ſettled Wits of <hi>Europe,</hi> were not eaſily removed out of the old Road and Track of Religion, whilſt the active and nimble Heads of the Eaſt were more deſirous of Novelties, more deſirous and cunning to invent Diſtinctions to cozen themſelves; more fluent in Language to expreſs their Conceits, as always Error groweth faſteſt in hotteſt Brains. Hence it came to paſs, the <hi>Melchites, Maronites, Neſtorians, Euticheans, Jacobites,</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread thoſe parts. Then it was (mark that) juſt with God, ſaith he, to ſuffer them that would not be convinced by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Counſel, to be ſubdued by the <hi>Pagans</hi> Sword. And again, ſaith he, it may juſtly ſeem Admirable, that that ſenſleſs Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſhould gain ſo much ground on Chriſtianiſm, eſpecially ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving neither real ſubſtance in Doctrine, nor winning behaviour in Ceremony, to allure Profeſſors; being but the ſcum of Juda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm and Paganiſm ſod together, here and there ſtrawed with a ſpice of Chriſtianity. Thus was fulfilled, what was written, on</q> thoſe that received not the love of the Truth, God gave them over to believe Lyes, and puniſhed them with the <hi>Pagans</hi> Sword; and being no whit bettered, then the Lord prepared the four Angels, or Meſſengers of his Wrath, whom <hi>John Napier,</hi> a Nobleman of <hi>Scoland,</hi> obſerveth to be the four <hi>Mabometan</hi> Nations, that inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit about, or beyond the River <hi>Euphrates;</hi> to wit, the <hi>Saracens, Turks, Tartarians,</hi> and <hi>Arabians,</hi> all Confederates together in one Law of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and under one great Emperour <hi>Ottoman,</hi> whom God for the Sins of Chriſtians, had prepared for an Hour, a Day, a Month, and a Year, to ſlay the third part of Men: By whom, ſaith the learned <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> God ſcourged Chriſtendom with Fire, Smoke, and Brimſtone, out of the Horſes Mouths, and Horſemen conducted by the Angel of Deſtruction. Yet the <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 9. 20.</note> Remnant of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102616:8"/> Men not killed by theſe Plagues, repented not of their Works, that they ſhould not worſhip Devils, and Idols of Gold and Silver, and Braſs, and Wood, and Stone, which can neither hear, nor ſee, nor walk. See <hi>Ainſworth Arrow, pag.</hi> 96.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the Judgments of God upon the Primitive Apoſtate Churches, ſome falling to <hi>Mahometiſm,</hi> others to <hi>Papiſtry,</hi> yet no Apoſtate Church retained more Idolatry than <hi>Rome;</hi> and that that Church is the great Whore, Myſtery <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the Beaſt that ſhe rideth on is the Popiſh Prelacy, is plainly ſhewed in the Anſwer of that famous Proteſtant <hi>H. Ainſworth,</hi> to <hi>John Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> the Papiſt: That whereas in their Letters written to each other, <hi>John Ainſworth</hi> ſaith, <q>The ſeven Mountains, in <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. are ſaid to be ſeven Kings, none of which agree with the Pope.</q> Yea, ſaith <hi>Henry Ainſworth,</hi> the ſeventh agrees very well; for the Woman is the great City <hi>Rome;</hi> the Beaſt, on which ſhe rideth, hath ſeven Heads, which are expounded there to be ſeven Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and ſeven Kings, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. 3, 9. The ſeven Mountains are famous through the World, as <hi>Palatinus, Capitolinus, Aventinus, Eſquilinus, Caelius, Virminalis, Quirinalis,</hi> on which Mountains <hi>Rome</hi> was builded. The ſeven Kings are alſo ſeven Governments of <hi>Rome,</hi> renowned alſo in Hiſtories, as by <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cornel. Tacitus,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note> Kings, by Conſuls, by Decemviry, by Dictators, by Triumphiry, by <hi>Ceſars,</hi> by fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Emperours, and Popes; therefore when <hi>John</hi> wrote, the <hi>Five</hi> firſt <hi>were fallen,</hi> and removed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. 10. <hi>and one</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is,</hi> namely the <hi>Sixth</hi> by the <hi>Ceſars, and another is not yet come,</hi> which was the Foraign Emperours, as <hi>Trajan</hi> the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and the like, who when they come, ſhould <hi>continue but a while; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> going to <hi>Bizantium,</hi> and the Empire being over-run by the barbarous <hi>Goths; and the Beaſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is the eighth, and is one of the ſeventh,</hi> Rev. 17. 11. meaning the Popes, who by an Eccleſiaſtical Government differ from the Civil Emperours, and ſo are the eighth, yet becauſe they Reign together with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, they make as it were one Government; So the eighth is one of the ſeven, as the Scripture ſaith. Unto this agrees the words of St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> The Beaſt <note n="†" place="margin">Bernard. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 125.</note> that hath a Mouth ſpeaking Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, occupieth <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair.</p>
            <p>Moreover, ſaith the Scripture, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 18. <hi>Let him that hath underſtanding, count the number of the Beaſt, for it is the number of a Man, and his number is</hi> 666. Now for the better underſtanding of this Myſtery, we muſt know that it is the general Courſe of the Spirit of God throughout the <hi>Revelations,</hi> to take Words and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102616:8"/> Phraſes out of the Prophets, and apply them to the things there propheſied; as in this number of the Beaſt, which is by a borrowed ſpeech taken from the name of a Man and his Familie, in <hi>Ezra</hi> 2. 13. the Man's name being <hi>Adonikam,</hi> by ſignification, a <hi>God aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> or <hi>ſtanding up;</hi> his Sons were 666. Now the Beaſt by ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification is called <hi>a Man</hi> (to wit) <hi>of Sin,</hi> who by agreement with <hi>Adonikam</hi>'s name, is ſaid to be <hi>a God ſtanding up,</hi> or <hi>exalting himſelf above all that is called God,</hi> meaning above Chriſt, by his aſſuming into the Office of Chriſt, to give Laws or Directions in Worſhip, which only belongeth to Chriſt, the Prophet like unto <hi>Moſes;</hi> ſo was he faithful in all his Houſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 2.</p>
            <p>Now as in the Myſtical Body of Chriſt's Church, <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 14. 27.</note> many Members make one Body, or <note n="‖" place="margin">Eph. 3. 15.</note> Family, all honouring Chriſt the <note n="†" place="margin">Col. 1. 18.</note> Head of the Body, as Children do a Father, and ſerve God in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip by his Direction and Appointment, are therefore of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <note n="‖" place="margin">Acts 1. 25.</note> of his Name, called Chriſtians <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 11. 26. Iſa. 65. 15.</note>, do grow up in him unto a perfect Man, unto the Meaſure and Stature of the Fulneſs of Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 13, 15.</p>
            <p>Even ſo as the falſe Church is an Harlot, the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> the Pope being Head, their Lord, and Law-giver in Worſhip, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of many Members which ſerve and worſhip by his Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are joyned to that Harlot <note n="†" place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 15.</note>, together with her Head, the Pope, all make one Body, or <hi>Man</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2. 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>of Sin;</hi> ſo are they of the number of his <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 13. 18.</note> Name, as Children to their Reverend Father in God, making one Family with him; as the Sons of <hi>Adonikam</hi> 666, made one Family to their Father: and thus the number of the Beaſt is the number of a Man, by this borrowed ſpeech 666. So that in ſome reſpects the Beaſt may be likened to the Image <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> ſaw, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 31. The Pope with his Triple Crown, who is proclaimed for a Vice-God <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictus,</hi> printed at <hi>Bonenia. Anno.</hi> 1608. <hi>Hen. Ainſ.</hi> Animad. <hi>pag.</hi> 100.</note>, the Invincible Monarch of of the Common-wealth, and vehement Conſerver of the Popiſh Omnipotency, he is the Head of Gold; the Cardinals and Prelates are next to him, as Breſts and Arms of Silver; the other Belly-god Clergy, is the ſtrong brazen Panch; the Lay-People are as Legs and Feet of Iron and Clay, which carry and bear up the Bulk; and the unclean <note n="‖" place="margin">Rev. 16. 13, 14. 2 Theſſ. 2. 9.</note> ſpirit of Satan giveth life and effectual operation to the Beaſt: and to be a member of this their Body and Church, the Papiſts themſelves <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm. de</hi> Eccleſ. l. 3. c. 2.</note> profeſs that there is not any inward Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue required, ſo then there is no need of the Spirit of God to join the Limbs of the Beaſt together.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:102616:9"/>
            <p>Moreover, that theſe Popes are Beaſts, note farther what <hi>Henry Ainſworth</hi> ſaith to <hi>John Ainſworth</hi> the Papiſt, <q>Their Vows of Chaſtity being but to defile themſelves with vile Sodomy, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and Fornication. So that the ſix thouſand Childrens Heads found Murdered in Pope <hi>Gregory</hi>'s Fiſh-pond, made him reverſe his own wicked Decree, in reſtraining the Clergy from their Wives.</q> And again, ſaith <hi>John Traper,</hi> in his <hi>Treaſure of Holy Truths,</hi> Pag. 153. <q>That Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the <hi>10th,</hi> admiring the huge maſſes of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney which he had raked together by Fraud and Wile, ſaid to Cardinal <hi>Bembus, See what a deal of Wealth we have got by this Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Chriſt.</hi> And when the ſame <hi>Bembus</hi> brought a place of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</q> to comfort him, lying on his Death-bed, <hi>Away</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with theſe Bawbles,</hi> ſpeaking concerning Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Moreover, ſaith <hi>John Napier</hi> aforeſaid, on his Paraphraſe of the <hi>Revelation, Pag.</hi> 58. proved out of the Papiſts own Authors, That of Popes, thirteen were Adulterers, three were common Brothel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, four were Inceſtuous Perſons, eleven were poiſoned with So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domy, ſeven were Whoremongers, and Inventers of Brothel-Houſes; finally, one was a Whore, and died (being delivered of a Baſtard) in open Proceſſion.</p>
            <p>Now ſurely on thoſe People God hath ſent ſtrong Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that believe that theſe ſinful wicked Popes can pardon Sins, and give power to his Prieſts ſo to do, upon a falſe ground gathered from Chriſt's Words to <hi>Peter,</hi> Matth. 16. 19. <hi>Whatſoever thou ſhalt bind on Earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven; and whatſoever thou ſhalt looſe on Earth, ſhall be looſed in Heaven:</hi> When this Power be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth not to one Man; but when any obſtinate Sinner is caſt out of a true Church, and upon his repentance he is received in again; as it is written to the whole Church, <hi>To whom ye forgive any thing,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 10.</note> 
               <hi>I forgive:</hi> So that this Power is not given to one Man, but to every true Church of Chriſt in God's Order and Manner aforeſaid. But how is it poſſible that either the Popes, or the whole Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> can forgive Sins, when the preſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> cannot be proved a true Church, no, nor (in all likelihood) the Natural Poſterity of the Saints in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s time?</p>
            <p>Firſt, Conſidering the many Changes in the <hi>Roman</hi> State, <hi>ſo that</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 6. 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>Heaven departed, as a Scrowl when it is rouled together; and every Mountain and Iſland were moved out of their places: Kings, and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains fled, and hid themſelves:</hi> So great was the Judgment of God on the <hi>Roman</hi> Power for Murdering the Lord Jeſus, and after Perſecuting him in his Members.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:102616:9"/>
            <p>As for particulars, <hi>Alaricus</hi> with his <hi>Goths,</hi> in the Year of Chriſt 414, took <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hierony in Epiſt.</hi> See <hi>Henry Ainſw.</hi> Animad. <hi>p.</hi> 102, the many Authors quoted to prove it.</note> and ſpoiled <hi>Rome</hi> in burning it: Forty four Years after, <hi>Genſericus</hi> with his <hi>Vandals,</hi> took and ſpoiled it; ſo that <hi>Rome</hi> for a time remained without Inhabitants. Some Years after did <hi>Odoacer</hi> with another Company invade <hi>Italy,</hi> and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered <hi>Rome,</hi> and put the Emperour to flight, made himſelf King. Then <hi>Theodoricus,</hi> with the <hi>Oſtrogoths,</hi> took it; and after him again <hi>Belliſarius</hi> with his Army wan it: But above all, <hi>Totilus</hi> King of the <hi>Goths,</hi> in the Year of our Lord 546, after all the former In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions, did overthrow <hi>Rome</hi> quite, caſt down the Walls, burnt the Houſes, and made it ſo Deſolate, that there remained in it neither Man nor Woman. Theſe Turmoils in <hi>Rome</hi> within a few Years, and the poſſeſſing of that Land by Foreigners, as the <hi>Goths</hi> mixing themſelves with the People, degenerated into the name of <hi>Italians;</hi> afterwards the <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Blond.</hi> l. 2. d. 2. Faſcic. temp. f 66.</note> 
               <hi>Saracens</hi> killed innumerable People in <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Italy.</hi> All which may teach us how unpoſſible it is, that the preſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſo much as the Natural Stock of the Saints in <hi>Paul</hi>'s time; which if they were, can be no better than the <hi>Iſhmalites</hi> and <hi>Edomites,</hi> the natural ſtock of <hi>Abraham,</hi> could be juſtified to be the Church of God then, as <hi>Rome</hi> now; or the <hi>Amorites</hi> and <hi>Jebuſites</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Joſh. 10. 1.</note> in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> becauſe <note n="†" place="margin">Gen. 14. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> Prieſt of the moſt High God with his faithful company, lived there five or ſix hundred Years before, as well as the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, be now plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, becauſe above 1600 Years ago a true Church once lived there. Now let all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> judg, where is the Antiquity that the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church pleadeth ſo much for, unleſs it be old in Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? So that it is admirable, how any that owns the name of a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> can believe, that it is lawful to worſhip God by that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, that had the ſucceſſion of his Miniſtry from <hi>Popiſh</hi> Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>Therefore in the next place, let us take a view of the manner how they are made Prieſts in <hi>Rome,</hi> as themſelves have written. They are made Prieſts, when by the Biſhop (who only can give this Order) it is ſaid, <hi>Receive power to celebrate Maſſes, both for the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and for the Dead, and to offer Sacrifices unto God, in the Name of the Lord.</hi> The Biſhop ſaith withal, <hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> (Oh blaſphemous Speech!) The Prieſts are alſo ſhaven on their Crowns, and anointed with Oyl on their Hands, that by that <note n="‖" place="margin">See <hi>Hen. Ainſw.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim adver. <hi>p.</hi> 61. Bellarm. <hi>Pontifical. Lib. de Ordinat. Presbit.</hi>
               </note> Unction and the Biſhops bleſſing, thoſe Hands may be Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and Sanctified of God. A Stole of Innocency is put upon the Prieſt, and he promiſeth to the Biſhop and his Succeſſors, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102616:10"/> and Obedience, and the Biſhop gives him again the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, that he may be bleſſed in his Prieſtly Order, and may offer placable Hoſts (or Sacrifices) to God for the Sins of the People. This Ordination hath a double effect: Firſt, A perpetual Spiritual Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, in ſign whereof a Character (or Mark) indelible is imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on them. And ſecondly, Grace, making them acceptable, whereby they are inabled to execute their Office. So this Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ordination conferreth Grace. And if any ſhall ſay, That the Holy Ghoſt is not hereby given, <hi>Let him</hi> (ſaith the Council of <note n="*" place="margin">Seſſ. 23. Can. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Trent) be accurſed.</hi> Now judge ye, <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> whether this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation do not make Men more like <note n="†" place="margin">Zech. 11. 17.</note> Idol-Shepherds, (being the very mark of the Beaſt) than Miniſters of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Now that we may the better diſcern how contrary to Nature and Grace this way of making Goſpel-Miniſters by this <hi>Romiſh</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, let us take a view of the true Way, how all true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters come to their Office by the Rules of Chriſt's Goſpel. Firſt, Every true Church is likened to a Virgin <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 11 2.</note>, who by the Covenant of the Goſpel is eſpouſed <note n="†" place="margin">Iſa. 62. 5. Eph. 5. 23.</note> to Chriſt her Head and Husband, and is ſaid in her firſt Conſtitution to have no <note n="‖" place="margin">Cant. 8. 8.</note> Breſts, that is, Miniſters: but in proceſs of time her Breſts are ſaid to be <note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. 16. 7. 1 Tim. 3. Iſa. 66. 11.</note> faſhioned, by the Lord's fitting ſome of her Members with Gifts, Graces, and Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications for the Work of the Miniſtry; which ſo ſoon as the whole Body, or Church, finding fit, do by common <note n="†" place="margin">Acts 1. 26.</note> conſent Elect <note n="‖" place="margin">&amp; 6. 13. Acts 14. 23.</note>, and after Faſting and Prayer, by what Member the Church thinketh fit for her Mouth, on the Lord's Day in the time of Government, do or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain the Perſon before Elected, ſome of the Fathers of Families lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Hands <note n="*" place="margin">Numb. 8. 9.</note> on the perſon Elected, in ſign, and for no other end, in the preſence of the whole Church, or Body, they are to take Charge of: That they are not only firſt Elected by common Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but by common Conſent are now ordained by that particular Church, or Body, they are to abide with whilſt Life doth <note n="†" place="margin">Acts 20 28.</note> laſt. And this is the true Elderſhip, or Miniſtry, the Lord hath given to every particular true Church; (as <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to <hi>Titus)</hi> as I have appointed thee *. Which way of making Miniſters, is both agreeable, firſt to the <note place="margin">Tit. 1. 5.</note> Word of Grace, and alſo to the Order of Nature, that Miniſters, or Breſts, ſhould grow or proceed out of their own Bodies; and not like <hi>Romes</hi> Ordination, for Breſts, or Miniſters, to be made by a Biſhop, without the knowledg of the particular Body whereof they are to take Charge, and afterwards by unnatural Art ſet to the Body by the Biſhop's order, it may be, without the Peoples con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, whether they will or no, as no Natural, but an Artificial
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102616:10"/> Breſt, or Eye, to that Body ſo entring into their Office contrary to Grace, and order of Nature, not entring by the Door of Chriſt's Appointment, are compared to Thieves, Robbers, and Hirelings; <note place="margin">John 10.</note> who ſo ſoon as they hear of a bigger Benefice, being not by Grace and Nature in the Body, but only ſtuck on, they ſlide away, let the Flock ſhift how they can. Oh dear Proteſtants! Shall the Lord always wink at this Confuſion among you? No ſure: He will bring his Judgments ſpeedily, if it be not amended.</p>
            <p>Now having laid theſe things before you, let us in the next place obſerve, that there was a time fixed by the Lord, how long the Beaſt, or falſe Eccleſiaſtical State, ſhould generally reign over the Nations; to wit, by the ſpace of a thouſand Years. Which <note place="margin">Rev. 20. 4.</note> time, as <hi>John Napier</hi> hath Calculated the Prophetical Dates in the Prophets and the <hi>Revelations</hi> together, That the Beaſt's reign be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan <note place="margin">See <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier,</hi> on Rev. 10.</note> about the Year of our Lord 113, and 115, about which time the firſt Pope was ſet up, and ſo Poyſon was brought into the Church, and ſo continued their general Reign till about the Year 1541. And then, ſaith <hi>Napier,</hi> the ſeventh Angel began to ſound, at which time, ſaith the Angel, there ſhall be Time no longer; meaning, that the Rod of the Wicked ſhould not always reſt on the back <note n="†" place="margin">Pſal. 125.</note> of the Righteous: But all the Myſteries <note n="‖" place="margin">Rev. 10. 7. &amp; 8. 9.</note> in the Prophets ſhould be fulfilled, which laſt Myſtery in theſe latter Days, ſeemeth to be the call of the Lord's Elect <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 20. 5. Epheſ. 2. 1.</note>, dead in Sin, out of the Spiritual <hi>Babylon,</hi> or <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, according to the Myſtery, or Figure thereof, by the Lord's Call of his People out of the Temporal <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon.</hi> So that, as aforeſaid, the Way of God in the Revelation, is to take Words and Phraſes out of the Prophets, and to apply them to things of like nature, to be fulfilled in theſe laſt Days. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> did eat a little <note n="†" place="margin">Ezek. 3. 3.</note> Book, ſignifying thereby that he muſt Propheſie to the dry <note n="‖" place="margin">Ezek. 37.</note> Bones in Old <hi>Babylon;</hi> even ſo in theſe latter Days under the Perſon of <hi>John,</hi> muſt the Lord's Servants eat a little Book <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 10. 9.</note>, that is, Propheſie to the dead in Sin in the Spiritual <hi>Babylon,</hi> even among the many Nations, Peoples Tongues, and Kings. So that about the Year aforeſaid, 1541, came forth the eaters of the little Book, ſome of which were <hi>Luther, Calvin, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon;</hi> all under the name of an Angel <note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 14. 6.</note>, to preach the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel to every Nation, Kindred, Tongue, and People: By whoſe means, not only many People of all degrees ſaw how they had been deceived, but alſo Kings, by the Light of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, ſaw how their Senſes were ſtupified, and made Drunk with the Wine of the Whores Fornication: ſo that not only in other
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102616:11"/> Nations, but in this Nation alſo, the Kings who had long given their Power to the Beaſt, until the Words of God ſhould be fulfilled, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 17. began to hate the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Whore, and the Beaſt that carried her, ſo that a part of the Beaſt's power out of this Land was deſtroyed, when the Cardinals, Jeſuits, and others aforenamed were Aboliſhed: By which means the power of the Beaſt was abated, and more of the Lord's Servants came boldly forth <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 7. 14.</note> out of great Tribulations, all ſignified by an Angel flying through the midſt of Heaven, to Preach the Everlaſting <note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 14. 6.</note> Goſpel unto them that dwell on the Earth: So that by this time, the Temple of God was opened in Heaven <note n="‖" place="margin">Rev. 11. 19.</note>, and the Ark of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, meaning God's Law, clearly ſeen in the truth thereof; as was ſignified by the Lightnings, and Voices, and Thunderings, which wrought ſuch an Earthquake among the Antichriſtian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, that the tenth <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11. 13.</note> part of the City fell, meaning the great City, the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, that Reigned over the Kings of the Earth, to the number of God's Elect in <hi>Iſrael</hi> 7000; of which number of Faithful, Elect, Precious, Living Stones, were many famous Churches eſtabliſhed in <hi>England, Scotland, France, Germany, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and other parts, to the great joy of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus according to the Myſtery ſignified to <hi>Zechariah,</hi> by a Man with a <note n="†" place="margin">Zach. 2. 1, 2. Ezek. 40. 2, 3, 5.</note> Meaſuring-Line in his Hand, ſignifying that <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> ſhould be built, the ſecond Temple in it, and God's true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip reſtored, as was done in the days of <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah.</hi> Even ſo, according to the Figure, was it ſhewed to <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11. 1.</note> 
               <hi>John,</hi> by a Reed given him to meaſure the Temple of God, the Altar and Worſhippers; that God's Temple of living Stones, and holy Truth, and Order of Worſhip, ſhould be reſtored by a Call of the Lord's People out of the Spiritual <hi>Babylon,</hi> in theſe latter Days, as aforeſaid. So that as <hi>Judah,</hi> their Figure, muſt ſeparate themſelves from all the <note n="†" place="margin">Ezra. 6. 21.</note> filthineſs of the old <hi>Babylonians</hi> in Worſhip, in ſo much that they admitted no Man to the work of the Prieſthood, but ſuch as could prove their <note n="*" place="margin">Neh. 7. 64.</note> Chronology according to God's Law; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuffer any Prieſt that had fallen down before an Idol, never <note n="†" place="margin">Ezek. 44. 12, 13.</note> more to Adminiſter in the Prieſts Office, becauſe they were Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of Chriſt our High Prieſt in his Office: Even ſo the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Chriſtian Proteſtants, by the number 7000, would not take a Stone of <hi>Babylon</hi> for a Corner <note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 5. 26.</note>, or for a Foundation; that is, any one to be their Miniſter, by virtue of <hi>Romes</hi> Ordination; becauſe the Miniſters under the Goſpel, that enter not into their Miniſtry by the Door of Chriſt's Ordination, as afore ſhewed, are accounted by Chriſt but Thieves, and Robbers. So that as Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102616:11"/> not defiled with Women (or the devices of falſe Churches) <note place="margin">Rev. 14. 1, 4. Heb 12. 22</note> ought all thoſe to be that follow the Lamb Chriſt Jeſus, on Mount <hi>Sion;</hi> no more bearing the Beaſt's <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 13.</note> mark in ſerving God by Mens devices, but the <note n="†" place="margin">Iſa. 42. 4. Mat. 12. 21.</note> Name or Law of Chriſt in their Fore-heads, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Lord in Worſhip by the Appointment of the Lord Jeſus only. As it is written, <hi>This is my beloved Son, hear him,</hi> Luke 9. 35.</p>
            <p>Moreover, dear Proteſtants, note that in the Earthquake afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, there were beſides the 7000 aforeſaid, a Remnant <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11. 13.</note>, who ſeeing and hearing the powerful Doctrine of true Faith in Chriſt, <hi>Temperance, and Judgment to come,</hi> like <hi>Felix,</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Act. 24 25</note> 
               <hi>trembled;</hi> or, as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>were affrighted,</hi> to ſee the great Power of God in the work of Converſion: Of 7000, with <hi>Caleb</hi> and <note n="†" place="margin">Num. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord fully, <hi>gave Glory to the God of Heaven,</hi> as ſome in <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 13. but durſt not joyn themſelves with them, yet by the ſmall glimps of the Light they ſaw, they began to take their Journey towards <hi>Sion,</hi> after the fore-named Chriſtians: But in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 12. 14. Ezek. 20. 35. Gal. 1. 16.</note> of this World, meeting with ſome Croſſes and Troubles in the Fleſh for Chriſt's ſake, began to reaſon with Fleſh and Blood, like ſome <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> whether God were able to furniſh a Table in the <note n="‖" place="margin">Numb. 11. 4.</note> Wilderneſs? So theſe having received the Seed of God's Word on a Rock, had no root <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 8. 13.</note>; (that is, having no more Love to Chriſt, than to any Worldly Joy or Pleaſure) in time of Temptation fell away. So that they would go no farther than the King, and the moſt went in that Day, not willing to ſuffer any more for Chriſt's ſake; were content to go ſo far as to have the Pope's Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, Lord Abbots, Cardinals, Jeſuits, Monks and Friars, expelled the Land, but ſtaid there, and ſat down in the mid-way between <hi>Sion</hi> and <note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 18. 4</note> 
               <hi>Babylon</hi> or <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11. 8</note> 
               <hi>Egypt,</hi> under a part of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Miniſtry and Service-Book, ſome of the groſſeſt things being wiped out: And this was the ſtate of many <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, (as may be ſeen at this day) as is alſo confirmed by Mr. <hi>Fox,</hi> in the <hi>Acts and Monuments</hi> of thoſe Times; ſome of which Report is as followeth, <hi>Acts and Monuments, Edit.</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 1180, 1181, 1184. The Prieſts and Clergy that yielded to the King's Laws were ſuffered to keep their Places and Livings. After this, the King appointed the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> with other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, to make one convenient and meek Order, Rite, and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Common-Prayer, and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, who did ſo: Then in the next Parliament following, it was agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that all Miniſters in the Realm, ſhould be bound to ſay and uſe the Mattines, Even-Song, Celebration of the Lord's Supper, in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102616:12"/> ſuch Order and Form, as was contained in the ſaid Book, and not otherwiſe. Now becauſe ſome ſmall Alteration was made, Complaint was made, how <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> 1186.</note> by the cloaked Contempt, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Winking, and ſtubborn diſobedience of the Biſhops, and old Popiſh Curates, the Book of Common-Prayer was long after the publiſhing of the ſame, either not known at all, or elſe very irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently uſed through many places of the Realm. Yet was there no great cauſe why the People ſhould ſo deſpiſe it: for, as the King anſwered the Rebels in <hi>Devonſh.</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> 1189.</note> If the Service was good in <hi>Latin,</hi> it remained good in <hi>Engliſh;</hi> for nothing was altered, but to ſpeak with Knowledg, that which was ſpoken in Ignorance.</p>
            <p>And thus we ſee, that theſe Proteſtants did not ſeparate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves fully in coming out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſo as to <note n="‖" place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 17. Iſa. 52. 11. Rev. 18. 4.</note> 
               <hi>touch none of their unclean things,</hi> as God's Word commanded; but ſat down under a part of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Miniſtry and Service, with many other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices: For it was neither Chriſt nor his Apoſtles that appointed Prieſts Apparel, as long Gowns, Tippits, four horned Caps, but, as <note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Hen. Ainſw.</hi> Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyſon, <hi>pag.</hi> 234, 235. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of ſundry Authors.</note> Writers ſay, did Pope <hi>Zachary;</hi> nor white Linnen Surplices to wear at Service-time, as did Pope <hi>Silveſter;</hi> nor ringing of Bells to call the People to hear Service, as did Pope <hi>Sabiniam;</hi> and to make up the Muſick, Pope <hi>Vitalian</hi> brought in the Organs; and if theſe, or other Popes had brought in to the Worſhip under the Goſpel the 120 Trumpets <note n="†" place="margin">2 Chron. 5. 12.</note>, and other Inſtruments of Muſick uſed in the Ceremonial Worſhip under the Law, as well as Prieſts Garments would it not have bin as lawful to have uſed them? Yea, but <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> ſhould not be unmindful how that Chriſt by his Death, abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed all the Ceremonial Figurative Ordinances <note n="‖" place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 15.</note> out of his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as alſo the Inſtruments of Muſick, and hath made or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 21. 5.</note> all things new in Worſhip, a new Miniſtry, new Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, new Maintenance, new time and order for Goſpel-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: So was Chriſt faithful in his own Houſe, or Church, as a Son <note n="†" place="margin">Heb. 3. 5, 6.</note>, as was <hi>Moſes</hi> being but a Servant. So, that whoſoever profeſſeth to bear the Name of a Proteſtant, or true Chriſtian, may remember what is written to them; <hi>A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up unto you of your Brethren, like unto me, him ſhall ye hear</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Acts 3. 22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>in all things whatſoever he ſhall ſay unto you: And every Soul that will not hear that Prophet</hi> (to wit, Chriſt Jeſus) <hi>ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed from among the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to conclude with theſe Proteſtants, under the performance in Worſhip of ſo many Popiſh Devices, let us hear what ſome of the Martyrs have ſealed with their Bloods, whoſe Tombs they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102616:12"/> garniſh with their approving their Sufferings as true Martyrs of Jeſus. <hi>John Wickliff</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Acts and Monum. <hi>Edit.</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 114.</note> ſaith, <hi>That the Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, Dians, be the Diſciples of Antichriſt.</hi> William Swenderby <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 431.</note> ſaith, <hi>That the Pope, Cardinals, Biſhops, Prelates, making Laws contrary to Chriſt's Living, and his Laws, or any other ground put in Ruling the Church of Chriſt, but by Chriſt and his Laws, is very Antichriſt, Adverſaries to Chriſt and his Apoſtles. Sir</hi> John Old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle <hi>(Lord</hi> Cobham) ſaith <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 518.</note>, <hi>The Prieſts, Prelates, and Monks, are the very Body of the great Antichriſt; and that the Poſſeſſions, and Lordſhips of the Clergie, are the Venom of</hi> Judas <hi>ſhed into the Church. John Claidon,</hi> burnt in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 588.</note> profeſſed, <hi>That the Arch-Biſhops, Lord-Biſhops, Arch-Deacons, Deans, Parſons, Vicars, and the reſt of that ſort, are the Diſciples of Antichriſt, the very Antichriſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi> Now though theſe Men be dead, yet with <hi>Abel</hi> they <note n="†" place="margin">Heb. 11. 4.</note> ſpeak, and their Blood with all the Martyrs that have Suffered for the Teſtimony of Jeſus, crieth for <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 18. 7, 8. Rev. 6. 9, 10.</note> Vengeance againſt all that uphold that Popiſh Prelacy. Therefore, as one chief Reaſon among others that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was deſtroyed, was for the Sins of her Prophets, and Iniquities of her <note n="†" place="margin">Lam. 4. 13.</note> Prieſts, that have ſhed the Blood of the Juſt in the midſt of her: Therefore, O <hi>England!</hi> by this be warned who they are that haſten thy Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Now we have ſeen what a lame Reformation was here made by many thouſand Proteſtants, when they came out of Spiritual <hi>Egypt,</hi> (for ſo the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church is called, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. 8.) having utterly forgot, or elſe for fear, regarded not the Word of the Lord to God's People of Old, when they came out of Temporal <hi>Egypt; After the doings</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Lev. 18. 2, 3. with Deut. 12. 30, 31, 32.</note> 
               <hi>of the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>ſhall ye not do;</hi> as is fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewed, and written for our <note n="‖" place="margin">Rom. 15. 4.</note> Learning. So that inſtead of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fully ſeparated to touch no unclean thing, yet a part of the <hi>Romiſh Egyptian Miniſtry</hi> of Lordly Prelates was imbraced, and the Service aforeſaid by Law of overſight eſtabliſhed, ſo that there was another falſe Eccleſiaſtical State, neither Spiritual nor Civil, ſet up, to the great diſhonour of Chriſt's Spiritual State, and the Civil State, or Government in the Nation: And hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaith <hi>John, I beheld another Beaſt</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 13. 11.</note> 
               <hi>coming out of the Earth,</hi> (therefore not from Heaven) <hi>having two Horns like a Lamb,</hi> as if he were the only Vican of Chriſt (as the Pope pretends) on Earth. And who more than they againſt the Pope, until (as aforeſaid) the Civil Power had eſtabliſhed them by Law? And thereby Life was given to the very Image of the Pope, the firſt Beaſt, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were ſo near a-kin, as a Child is to the Father, begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102616:13"/> after his own Image or likeneſs, which was not only ſo in its like falſe Eccleſiaſtical State, but alſo in Mind and Quality, and therefore this ſecond Beaſt is ſaid; by the Spirit of God, not only to ſpeak like a Dragon, but to <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 12.</note> exerciſe all the power of the firſt Beaſt before him, cauſing the Earth, and them that dwell therein, to worſhip the firſt Beaſt, by retaining a Miniſtry and Service, and other things, in Worſhip of his deviſing, very little refined, but ſtill of the ſame nature: So that no Man might Buy nor Sell, ſave thoſe that had the Mark of the Beaſt in their Fore-head, or Hands; that is, yield profeſſed Obedience to his Commands, in Worſhip to God by Law eſtabliſhed, whether they had Faith or no.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord in his Mercy towards this Nation, that was ſcarce come half out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſent others of his Servants under the name of another <note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 14. 8.</note> Angel, declaring to all Proteſtants, both Prince and People, that <hi>Babylon is fallen;</hi> and for more certainty again, ſaying, <hi>It is fallen:</hi> That ſo they might come fully out from all her devices in Worſhip, and ſo might no <hi>longer</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Rev. 18. 4.</note> 
               <hi>partake of her Sins, leſt they receive of her Plagues.</hi> But ſo ſoon as this falſe Eccleſiaſtical State, or <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 13.</note> ſecond Beaſt, perceiving with <note n="†" place="margin">Acts 19. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Demetrius,</hi> that if Chriſt's true Miniſtry and Government, as it was in the Primitive Days, of <note n="‖" place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 11.</note> Paſtors, Teachers, Elders, and Deacons, were imbraced, their gain of <hi>Shrine-making,</hi> (or keeping People in Ignorance what the true Miniſtry, Government, and holy Order of Chriſt's Kingdom of Worſhip is) would be loſt, and their Princely Revenues by the King, (as their Elder Brethren, Lord-Abbots, Cardinals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by former Kings) be converted to Charitable Uſes; and they (if they had any Grace) muſt by laborious Preaching, live of the free <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 7</note> Gift of the Flock they feed, and Vineyard they dreſs, when they had degraded themſelves by repentance of their falſe Miniſtry; and the People, if they thought fit, to Elect and Ordain them in God's Order, into the Work of the Miniſtry. But this was ſo contrary to theſe Prelates minds, that they ſent forth their Purſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to take and bring before them all that ſhould either refuſe to come to their Worſhip, or did ſpeak againſt their Miniſtry. So that in the Year 1592 <note n="†" place="margin">As was mentioned in a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Parlament at that time.</note>, on a Lord's Day, they took to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of fifty ſix Perſons, as they were ſerving God according to Chriſt's Directions in his laſt Will and Teſtament, (in the very place the like Chriſtians were forced to ſerve God in Queen <hi>Marie's</hi> days) and ſent them by two and two into the ſeveral Priſons in and about <hi>London;</hi> ſome of which by long Impriſonment were near Starved, others were Bapiſhed, and three they Hanged, two
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102616:13"/> at <hi>Tiburn,</hi> namely, Mr. <hi>Henry Barrow,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Greenwood;</hi> and Mr. <hi>John Penry</hi> was hanged at <hi>Thomas a Watering</hi> near <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark,</hi> in the Year 1593. That theſe were true <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to any that have, or ſhall read Mr. <hi>Barrow</hi>'s <hi>Diſcovery,</hi> his Anſwer to <hi>Gifford;</hi> Mr. <hi>Barrow</hi>'s and Mr. <hi>Greenwood</hi>'s Conference in Priſon with ſeveral Perſons; beſide all their Examinations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord Treaſurer, and ſome Juſtices; all Printed at that time: So that they were put to Death contraty to Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Mind, as was then ſpecified in Print <note n="*" place="margin">As was afterwards noted in an Apology preſented to King <hi>James</hi> by the ſame Church.</note>, becauſe ſhe ſent her Reprieve two ſeveral times to fetch them back when they were carrying to be Executed; but contrary to her knowledg (it may be ſuppoſed) were they at laſt put to Death, ſooner than the ordinary time a day, by means of the Prelates; as I find in a certain printed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of their Sufferings, in theſe words: Mr. Barrow, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Greenwood, <hi>were put to Death by the Prelates, in Queen</hi> Elizabeth's <hi>Time, without her knowledg or privity; and that early in the Morning, the figure of their Sufferings being ſeen in the Skie by Mariners that were in other parts; and it was ſuppoſed by the beholders of the Figure, then to be done in</hi> England, <hi>becauſe of the Women wearing of Hats: The two poor Widows that attended upon them in the Priſon, waited on them to the Gallows, bearing their winding Sheets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, dear Proteſtants, if the Blood of God's Servants ſhed in King <hi>Manaſſes</hi> days, for bearing their Teſtimony againſt the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Men, ſet up in Worſhip, contrary to the Law of God written by <hi>Moſes,</hi> was charged near eighty Years after on their Poſterity, who followed the ſteps of their Fore-Fathers, in Perſecuting the Lord's Prophets for like Work in <hi>Jeremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi>'s <note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 15. 4.</note> days; and if the righteous Blood ſhed from the days of <hi>Abel</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Mat. 23. 35.</note>, was by Chriſt charged on the <hi>Jews</hi> for perſecuting him and his Diſciples, for telling them they <hi>worſhipped God in vain</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Mat 15. 9.</note>, <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Doctrine the Commandments of Men;</hi> how may Proteſtants now fear that the Lord may have like Indignation againſt this Nation, or Generation, for perſecuting the Lord's Servants, who call them from the Devices of Men in Worſhip, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God as he hath appointed by his Son Chriſt Jeſus in his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament?</p>
            <p>Now therefore, before the Judgment is poured on us, Oh that the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty would do the Work herein that belongeth to Kings, to aboliſh all Inventions (ſet up by other Kings) out of Worſhip; and every good Proteſtant to do his Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to touch none of the unclean <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 17.</note> things of Mens Inventions
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102616:14"/> in Worſhip! Then may we expect, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did when he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Church from all Idolatry, that God would turn the Hearts of Kings to be (as God hath ordained them) <note n="†" place="margin">Iſa. 49. 22.</note> Nurſing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the Lord's People, as <hi>Pharoah</hi> was to the Church in <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi>'s days: But when <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Poſterity after his Death had corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves with the Idols of <hi>Egypt,</hi> then God turned the Heart of King <hi>Pharoah</hi> to afflict them. So when all that go by the name of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> ſhall do as aforeſaid, God will turn the Hearts of Kings to them; and until this Work be done, God will make Kings the Rod <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 10 5.</note> of his Anger againſt a Hypocritical Nation; as he did the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and call them his Servants, as he did <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Jer. 25. 9.</note>, to afflict his People. Therefore let no Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, like Children, envy the Rod, but conſider the cauſe for which the Rod is prepared, and amend thoſe things that are amiſs, and God will break the Rod, and turn it againſt our Enemies; and then Kings will (as God hath ordained them) be Nurſing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to preſerve the Church of God from all Injuries and Wrongs, as it is written, <note n="‖" place="margin">Rev. 12. 16.</note> 
               <hi>The Earth helped the Woman;</hi> as is very excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewed by Mr. <hi>Penry,</hi> in his Examination before two Juſtices of the Peace, Mr. <hi>Fancha,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Young,</hi> in the Year 1593, <hi>April</hi> the <hi>10th,</hi> in his Anſwer to ſome Queſtions put to him. The firſt was this:</p>
            <p>Queſt. 1. <hi>You labour to draw her Majeſties Subjects from their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to her Laws, and from this Church of</hi> England, <hi>to hear you, and ſuch as you are, teach in Woods.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Mr. <hi>John Penry</hi>'s Anſwer:</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Nay, I perſuade all Men unto the Obedience of my Prince and her Laws: Only I diſſuade all the World from yielding obedience and ſubmiſſion unto the Ordinances of the Kingdom of Antichriſt, and would perſuade them to be ſubject to Chriſt, and his Bleſſed Laws, as I aſſure my ſelf that the ſame is warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereby: Her Majeſty having granted, (in Eſtabliſhing and Confirming the great Charter of <hi>England,</hi> whereunto, as I take it, the Kings and Queens of this Land are ſworn when they come to the Crown) That the Church of God under them, ſhould have all her Rights and Liberties inviolable for ever. Now let the benefit of this Law be granted unto me, and others of my Brethren, and it ſhall be found that we have done nothing but what is warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by her Laws.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>What, is it meet that Subjects ſhould charge their Prince to keep Covenants with them, and enter to ſcan what Oaths they have taken</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:102616:14"/> 
                  <hi>for this purpoſe? VVhere find you this warranted by Scripture?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Subjects are in a moſt lamentable caſe, if they may not alledg their Princes Laws for their Actions, yea, and ſhew what their Princes have promiſed to the Lord and to them, when the ſame may be for declaration of their Innocency. And it is the Crown and Honour of Princes, to be known not only to hold, but even to be in Covenant with their Subjects, that they will maintain and preſerve them from Violence and Wrong. Nay, Heathen Princes have thought themſelves honoured, when their mean Subjects have charged them very earneſtly with the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants whereby they were bound unto their People. The Laws of this Land are ſo full this way, as no Man converſant in them can be ignorant, that our Princes have preferr'd the obſerving of thoſe equal Covenants, whereby they are tied unto their People, before the accompliſhing of their own private Affections, yea, and Commandments in ſome Caſes. Hence it is that the Judges of this Land are bound by Law to adminiſter Juſtice and Equity unto the poor Subjects, notwithſtanding that the Prince's Letter be directed to them to the contrary. And as to the Law of God, all Kings and Princes are bound thereby, to be ſo far from thinking themſelves tied by no Bonds unto their Subjects, as they are plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forbidden to be <hi>lifted up in Mind above their Brethren,</hi> Deut. 17. 20. For ſo the word in that place, calleth their Subjects and Servants. The Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> who had the greateſt Priviledges and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives, both Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, over their People, that ever any Kings or Princes can have, (becauſe they were Types and Figures of that Great King of Kings, the Lord Jeſus) yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into Covenant notwithſtanding with their People, even par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, beſides the general former Law, whereby they were bound unto them. Yea, the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> being in no leſs danger and diſgrace with all Eſtates, than I and my Brethren are at this preſent, required his Soveraign Lord and King <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> to promiſe that he would do him no Violence nor Wrong, nor yet ſuffer others to do the ſame, for telling him the truth of the Word, in the things wherein the King required to be reſolved at his hands: The which thing <hi>Zedekiah</hi> yielded unto, and that by an Oath and Covenant of the Lord, <hi>Jer.</hi> 38. 15, 16. Whereby it appeareth, that it is not without great Warrant of the Lord, that Princes ſhould enter into Covenant with their Subjects, and that Subjects ſhould require Promiſe and Oath to be kept with them; otherwiſe, Whereto ſerveth the Covenant? But alas. I enter not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102616:15"/> to ſcan her Majeſties Oath, I only tell you what her Laws allow me, and my poor Brethren; and I am aſſured, if her Majeſty knew the equity and uprightneſs of our Cauſe, we ſhould not receive this hard meaſure which we now ſuſtain, ſeeing we and our Cauſe are never brought before her but in the odious weeds of Sedition, Rebellion, Schiſm, Hereſie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> therefore it is no marvel to ſee the edge of her Sword turned againſt us.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>Hath not her Majeſty by her Laws eſtabliſhed theſe Offices, and this Order that now is in the Church of</hi> England?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Her Laws have, I grant, of overſight, as taking them for the right Offices and Order which appertain unto the Church of Chriſt; which becauſe we evidently ſee that they are not, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore flie we unto her former Promiſe and Act, whereby ſhe grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us the enjoying of all the Priviledges of the Church of God.</p>
               <p>In the next place, There be other Proteſtants that have come yet farther out of the <hi>Romiſh Babylon,</hi> in diſclaiming the Service-Book, Surplice, Organs, Croſs in Baptiſm, Prieſts Garments, and the like, becauſe they were Popiſh: Yet it is to be admired, why ſuch cannot as well diſclaim the Order of the Miniſtry received from the Biſhops, as the Biſhops received it from the Pope, one Miniſter ordaining another without the Congregations knowledg where they are to take Charge; and likewiſe pay and receive Tithes for their Miniſters Maintenance, which Pope <hi>Paſcalis,</hi> 827 Years after Chriſt <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> 19. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus a populo.</hi>
                  </note>, firſt ordained for his Prieſts: Theſe Proteſtants can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think to eſcape the Judgments of God, who <note n="†" place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 17. Rev. 18. 4.</note> touch the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean things forbidden, and are not fully come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> as <hi>Judah</hi> our Figure was, who ſent away all <hi>Babylon</hi>'s filthineſs <note n="‖" place="margin">Ezra. 6. 2. Zech. 5. 8, 9, 11.</note> with the Wings of a Stork, into the Land of <hi>Shiner,</hi> or <hi>Babylon,</hi> where they were hatched, as afore-ſhewed.</p>
               <p>Moreover, There are other Proteſtants, who though they have forſaken the Miniſtry, Service, and all the fore-named <hi>Romiſh</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, yet they retaining the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Errors of Free-will, falling from true Grace, general Redemption, and denying that glorious Doctrine of Election, cannot think to eſcape the Judgments of God; becauſe Error in Faith is ſo heinous in the ſight of the Lord, being likened to Leaven <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 16. 6, 12. 1 Cor. 5.</note>, Darkneſs <note n="†" place="margin">Luke 11. 34. 35.</note>, and Poyſon <note n="‖" place="margin">Deut. 32. 3.</note>, that God threatned the Church of <hi>Pergamos,</hi> to fight againſt them, for not puniſhing them by Excommunication that maintained the Error, or Doctrine <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 2. 14, 16.</note> of <hi>Balaam;</hi> and the Church at <hi>Thyatira,</hi> for ſuffering the Women <hi>Jeſebel</hi> to teach <note n="†" place="margin">Ver. 20.</note>, and to deceive them: All which came on the Churches afore-ſhewed, in <hi>Pag.</hi> 13. alſo <hi>Junius,</hi> on <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 10.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:102616:15"/>
               <p>Again, There are other Proteſtants that are not guilty of the fore-named Errors, yet for other ſins of diſorder, in making <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 6. 4. Ex. 34 16. 1 Cor. 7. 39.</note> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages with them they cannot joyn with in the Ordinances of Worſhip, and their walking in the ſhame of Nature, long Hair <note n="†" place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 14.</note>, and Perriwigs; which Evils, as well as other ſinful Converſations not in God's Order puniſhed, the whole Church becomes <note n="‖" place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 22. Pſ. 26. 5, 6. Pro. 11. 21. Joſh. 22.</note> guilty of one anothers Sins: As ſaith the Law, <hi>Whatſoever the unclean Perſon toucheth, ſhall be unclean; and the Perſon that toucheth him, ſhall be unclean,</hi> Numb. 19. 22.</p>
               <p>Again, There are others that would be called they know not what, who refuſe the uſe of God's Ordinances in Worſhip; to wit, Baptiſm of Water, and the Lord's Supper, and ſuffer their Females <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 34, 35.</note> 
                  <hi>(Jeſebel</hi> like) to teach their Imaginations. For no Perſon can teach any other thing concerning God or Chriſt, in the work of Man's Redemption to Salvation, that own not the written Scripture as the <note n="†" place="margin">John 5. 39. Gal. 6. 16. 1 Kings 8. 25. with 2 Chron. 6. 16.</note> Ground of Faith, and the Rule to try all Doctrine and Worſhip by, who (as it is ſaid) do deny the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Body: Unto ſuch the Apoſtle hath ſaid, <hi>If the Body riſe not, then is not Chriſt riſen;</hi> and ſo to them, <hi>All Preaching is vain, and they are yet in their Sins</hi> 
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 14, 17.</note>, <hi>and of all Men moſt miſerable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another great miſtake is among many Proteſtants, in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Prophecies and Myſteries in the Prophets literally, concerning the Spiritual Glory of the Church under the Goſpel, or Chriſt's Reign with the Saints on Earth. I would fain have theſe Proteſtants firſt to remember, that Chriſt's Kingdom <note n="*" place="margin">John 18. 36.</note> is not of this World, neither the Warfare, nor Weapons <note n="†" place="margin">2 Cor. 10. 4.</note> Carnal; and in all things exemplary to the Church under the Goſpel, we are exhorted to behold <hi>Iſrael</hi> 
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 18.</note> our Figure. Firſt, In the Wilderneſs, figuring our Spiritual Warfare over Sin, the World, and the Devil; and then by <hi>Joſhua,</hi> as they were led into <hi>Canaan,</hi> the figure of <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 11. 13 14, 15.</note> Heaven. So the Saints in the Wilderneſs <note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 12. 6. Exod. 13. 14. chap. Ezek. 20. 35.</note> of this World, through many Tribulations <note n="‖" place="margin">Acts 14. 22.</note>, under the conduct of the true <hi>Joſhua,</hi> Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, enter into the glorious Reſt, even the Haven of Eternal Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs: And hereupon it is written in praiſe of Chriſt's <hi>Called, Choſen,</hi> and <hi>Faithful</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 17. 14.</note>, That all the thouſand Years Reign of the Beaſt, aforeſaid, they lived and reigned <note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 20.</note> with Chriſt, and they overcame him by the Blood of the Lamb, and by the Word of their Teſtimony, and that in the Wilderneſs, and this World; and the ſame is ſtill the Saints <note n="‖" place="margin">1 John 5. 4.</note> Victory, even our Faith, by which we overcome the World.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:102616:16"/>
               <p>Now as touching Election, that moſt Heavenly Doctrine of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to God's Children, for the help of them deceived about it, note. That Election is a Work of God the <note n="*" place="margin">Eph. 1. 4.</note> Father; Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 5. 9.</note> a Work of God the Son; and Sanctification <note n="‖" place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 11.</note> the Work of the Holy Ghoſt proceeding from the Father and the Son: So that the very nature of the word <hi>Election</hi> meaneth not all Men, but God fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing before all Time, in reſpect of Creation, whatſoever would come to paſs in time, did make choice of a Remnant <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 11. 5.</note> out of the Lump of Mankind, to be Heirs of Glory through Chriſt, and left the reſt in their fallen Eſtate: And who ſhall call God to account <note n="†" place="margin">Rom 9.</note> in theſe his Matters? So that whomſoever the Father Elected, he gave <note n="‖" place="margin">John 17. 12.</note> unto his Son to Redeem. And hereupon it is written in praiſe of God in Chriſt, <hi>Thou haſt Redeemed us</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 5. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>out of all Nations, Kindreds, Tongues, and People:</hi> So <hi>not all Nations,</hi> becauſe he was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a Ranſom for many: So that theſe <note n="‖" place="margin">Mat. 26. 28.</note> as <hi>many as were</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Acts 13. 48.</note> 
                  <hi>ordained to life, believed.</hi> For <note n="*" place="margin">Jo. 6 44.</note> no Man can come to Chriſt, but thoſe the Father draweth. Now if all had been Redeemed, the Altar under the Law, and Prieſts that ſerved at the ſame, (all Figures of Chriſt in the Work of Mans Redemption) would have ſignified ſo much in Chriſt the true Altar and High Prieſt, and Sacrifices offered thereon. So that if he had Redeemed all, would he not at the Golden Altar have offered up his Prayer for all? But as Chriſt redeemed only the <hi>Elect,</hi> or whole <note n="†" place="margin">Rom. 4. 1 Joh. 2. 2.</note> World <hi>Abraham</hi> was Heir of, ſo he appeared at the Golden Altar, to offer Prayers for no other but <note n="‖" place="margin">Rev. 8. 3, 4.</note> Saints; as it is written, <hi>I pray not for the World</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">John 17. 9, 20.</note>, <hi>but thoſe the Father had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him</hi> (in the <note n="†" place="margin">Ezek. 16. 8. Cant. 2 16</note> Covenant of Grace) <hi>out of the World.</hi> And thus all all that is Truth will agree to the Law (to wit) of Figures, and Teſtimony of the Goſpel of Salvation. And that thoſe Elected ones by God the Father, and Redeemed by Chriſt, cannot totally fall away, becauſe none can pluck them out of his Father's Hands <note n="‖" place="margin">John 10. 29.</note>, who has put his fear into their Hearts, that they ſhall not depart <note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 32. 40. Prov. 14. 26, 27.</note> from him: So are they kept by the Power <note n="†" place="margin">1 Pet. 1 5. John 17. 12.</note> of God through Faith unto Salvation, that they cannot poſſibly, ſaith Chriſt, be totally deceived, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 24.</p>
               <p>Now ſome will object, If the Elect cannot fall away; how came ſo many, as <hi>Demas,</hi> and the like, to fall from the Faith they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The Kingdom of Heaven is compared to a <note n="‖" place="margin">Mat. 13. 47, 48.</note> Draw-Net, which gathereth into it both good and bad; as in the Figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Building, among the Materials, came <note n="*" place="margin">1 Kings 10. 22.</note> Apes and Peacocks: So among the Elect Living Stones, the Materials of the Spiritual
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:102616:16"/> Building, came Hypocrites, who, like Apes, imitate for a time what the Saints do: Theſe are at the Feaſt, but want the Wedding <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 22. 11.</note> Garment of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, put on by Faith, having only Lamps of External <note n="†" place="margin">Mat. 25. 3.</note> profeſſion, or form of Godlineſs, and not the <note n="‖" place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 5.</note> Power, or Life thereof, the Oyl of God's Grace; ſo having received the Seed of God's Word on a Rock, wanting Root <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 8. 13.</note>, Faith that worketh by Love; ſo were in the Church (ſaith the <note n="†" place="margin">1 John 2. 19.</note> Scripture) but not of it; for had they been of it, no doubt they would have continued in it: Therefore, like Peacocks, through Pride fell away, not from Grace, but from that Grace they ſeemed <note n="‖" place="margin">Luke 8. 18.</note> to have; their <note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 22.</note> Swiniſh nature being never changed, turn again to wallow in the mire of open Filthineſs, as a Dog to their Vomit.</p>
               <p>As touching Free-will in Man in his fallen Eſtate, to repent, and turn from Sin to God, is a groſs miſtake. Firſt, Becauſe if <hi>Adam</hi> the Root had not this Power, how came his Children to have it? For cover <note n="†" place="margin">Job 31. 33.</note> his Sin he did, but repent he could not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not a virtue in Nature: As it is written, <hi>If God perad venture will give them Repentance</hi> 
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>to the acknowledgment of the Truth, who only works in his Elect, both to will</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 2. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>and to do of his good Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi> Therefore, when <hi>Eſau</hi> ſought Repentance with Tears, he found it not; becauſe true Repentance is a change <note n="†" place="margin">Heb. 12. 17.</note> of the Mind, which only belongeth to God to do: As by the gift of Faith, he opened the <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 16. 14.</note> Heart of <hi>Lydia</hi> to believe, and obey the Truth as it is in Jeſus, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 21.</p>
               <p>Some will object, If all Men have not power to believe and obey, why is it required of all Men?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As Belief is a point of Obedience to God our Creator, upon the Covenanted Eſtate Angels and Men made with God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Fall, it is ſtill applied unto all as the word of their Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: And hereupon <hi>Noah</hi> by his Preaching condemneth <note n="†" place="margin">Heb. 11. 7.</note> the old World, as it is ſtill the ſavour of Death unto Death, in them that periſh <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 15, 16.</note>: Elſe Chriſt would not have ſaid to the fallen Angel, <hi>It is written, Thou ſhalt worſhip</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Mat. 4. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve:</hi> So that as this was ſpoken to Satan, being what the Law required of him, yet it doth not therefore follow, that he had power to repent and believe; ſo can no Man. Though the ſame <note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 6. 13.</note>. Law requireth Obedience of all, yet none can believe and obey but the Elect, whom God giveth <note n="†" place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 25.</note> Repentance to: and to them only the Word is the ſavour of Life unto them that are ſaved by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus. Yet the Preacher knowing not who
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102616:17"/> are the Elect, doth apply the Word as generally, calling all Perſons to believe and obey in his Meſſage. As ſaith the Lord to <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſent him to <hi>Corinth, I have much People in this City:</hi> So <note place="margin">Act. 18. 10. John 10. 20.</note> not all, for they could not all believe, becauſe they were not all Chriſt's Sheep, as it is written, <hi>All Men have not Faith,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 3. 2.</p>
               <p>For theſe and the like errors in Faith, and corruption in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (which were too tedious here to refute) about the ſtate of Infant-Baptiſm, and the Seventh-day Sabbath; of the groſs miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in them that deny the one, and keep the other, (largely handled by me, not long ſince printed in a Book, intituled, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Truth Revived:</hi> Wherein is alſo in 22 Articles, every true Proteſtant's Faith inſerted, the State of a true Church, and how every Ordinance, and by whom, and in what Order they were performed in the Primitive Churches, containing ſix Sheets of Paper, unto which I refer the Reader) is one cauſe why God hath not before this deſtroyed the falſe Eccleſiaſtical power of the <hi>Romiſh Babylon:</hi> becauſe as the Sins of God's People of old, were the cauſe why old <hi>Babylon</hi> was not ſooner deſtroyed; even ſo is it <note place="margin">See and read Jer. 25.</note> now. That as then God did firſt give his own People a Cup to drink, and then <hi>Shiſhack</hi> did drink after them: So Judgment muſt firſt begin at the Houſe <note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 17.</note> of God, unleſs there be a ſpeedy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. Elſe ſurely the time is come, as that Servant of God Mr. <hi>Beal</hi> hath noted on <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. in his Book called <hi>The Image of both Churches,</hi> 
                  <q>That when the 1000 Years of the Beaſt's Raign was expired, Satan the common Adverſary of Man, ſhall be looſed out of his dark Priſon, and ſet at large by the ſufferance of God; Mans wickedneſs deſerving no other, ſtrongly deluding the Unbelievers for their unbelief-ſake, to deceive the Univerſal People of the World, through the operation of Errors: He ſhall cauſe them to give credance to Lyes, that they may be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for refuſing the Truth: So that the abomination of Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſhall be ſet up in the holy Place (meaning in the Heart, where Chriſt by faith ſhould dwell) to the utter deſtruction of Faith. Which People of him thus deluded, is called in a myſtery <hi>Gog and Magog;</hi> that is as much as to ſay, <hi>Covered,</hi> and <hi>Off-covered:</hi> For both the grand Captains of them depending, doth theſe two words comprehend, the one covering the Devil with many falſe Religions, (meaning, <hi>Loe, here is Chriſt, and loe, there is Chriſt);</hi> the other in his ſort following the ſame wicked conſent, theſe two Tyrants, the <hi>Romiſh Pope,</hi> and <hi>Mahomet,</hi> with the whole generation of like Spirits with them, (mark that) have ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered</q>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:102616:17"/> themſelves together againſt God and his Chriſt, to deſtroy the whole face of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>Now the woful experience of the beginning of theſe things is ſeen among us, ſo that our Condition looketh too like the ſtate of the <hi>Jews.</hi> When <hi>Titus Veſpaſian,</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor, came and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the <hi>Jews,</hi> by reaſon of their many Errors, were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into ſundry <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark</hi> 12. 13, 18.</note> Sects, and their dividing in Faith, divided them in Heart, that they deſtroyed one another: So the words of Chriſt were fulfilled on them that deſpiſed his Counſel, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Every Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf, is brought to deſolation.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 25.</note> How then doth it behove all Proteſtants to be by Chriſt's Words warned with ſpeed to examine whether they be in the Faith of God's Elect <note n="*" place="margin">Tit. 1. 1. Heb. 11.</note>, and worſhip God by Chriſt's <note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 14.</note> directions only; that there be no dividing in Judgment, and ſo not in Heart; conſidering what <note n="*" place="margin">In his Book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Card</hi> and <hi>Compaſs of Life,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to Prince <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt.</note> one hath noted, That the <hi>Jews</hi> affirm the firſt Blood ſplit in the World, was by reaſon of the differences in Judgment among Brethren (for ſo all that bear the name of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> ought to be) in theſe words: Cain <hi>was ſo poſſeſſed with Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, that he believed there was no Life after this: But</hi> Abel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved there was after this Life a reward for the Good, and puniſhment for the VVicked; in which Contention, Cain <hi>ſlew</hi> Abel. So that <hi>Cain</hi> was of the Wicked one: For, to Perſecute, Impriſon, or kill any one for Conſcience ſake, is a work <note n="†" place="margin">1 John 3. 12. Rev. 2. 10.</note> of the Devil, and a Wo is pronounced againſt them: As it is written, <hi>Wo to them that follow the way of</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Jude ver. 11.</note> Cain, <hi>they ſhall periſh.</hi> So that Proteſtants may be aſhamed to own that evil Spirit, to force Men to believe, when it is written, <hi>That it is God ſhall</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Gen. 9. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>perſwade</hi> Japhat <hi>to dwell in the Tents of</hi> Shem. Therefore to force Men to believe or practiſe in things Divine before God giveth them Faith, is but to make a Church of Hypocrites, whoſe Sacrifice is <note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 15. 8.</note> Abomination to the Lord, as their Father <hi>Cain's</hi> was.</p>
               <p>Now if any Proteſtant ſhould be offended, (like <note n="*" place="margin">Amos chap 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Amaziah</hi> the Prieſt of <hi>Bethel)</hi> with this Chriſtian Warning-piece, (as he was with the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi>'s Warning to King <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and his People, and ſay, <hi>The Land cannot bear theſe words)</hi> againſt the Inventions of Men in the Worſhip of God, &amp; charge me, as <hi>Amaziah</hi> did <hi>Amos</hi> the Prophet, with Conſpiracy againſt the King, when but for decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the only means then, from the immediate Mouth of the Lord, to preſerve the King and the Nation, as this is from the mediate written Word of God to preſerve our King and the Nations, from the Judgments threatned: I ſay, if we (like them) will regard no
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102616:18"/> Chriſtan Counſel, (all Scripture being written for our Admonition) then in all likelihood the Judgments threatned on them, will fall upon us, that <hi>God will darken</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Amos chap. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>the Earth in a clear day, by ſending a Famine in the Land, not of Bread, nor thirſt for Water, but of hearing the Words of the Lord.</hi> For by reaſon of ſo many falſe Teachers in <hi>Judah, their Silver became</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Iſa. 1 22.</note> 
                  <hi>droſs, their Wine was mixt with Water, and they were fed with</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 23. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Chaff inſtead of Wheat.</hi> As is now ſeen by woful experience, whilſt God's Word is not truly Taught, but corrupted with Errors, under the colour of Chriſtianity, with <hi>Lo, here is Chriſt, and lo, there;</hi> as they ſaid of old, <hi>The Temple of the</hi> 
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">Jer. 7. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, the Temple of the Lord are theſe:</hi> Nevertheleſs, they were told, <hi>Thy Prophets</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Lam. 2. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>have ſeen vain and fooliſh things for thee; for they have not diſcovered thine Iniquities to turn away thy Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, but have ſeen for thee falſe Burdens, and cauſes of Baniſhment.</hi> Oh that Proteſtants would lay theſe things to Heart, conſidering the many ſigns of God's diſpleaſure ſhewed againſt this Nation, of a Captivity threatned for theſe Sins: Witneſs the <hi>Spaniſh Invaſion,</hi> in 1588, then the <hi>Powder Plot,</hi> in 1605; the late <hi>Dreadful Plague</hi> and <hi>Fires;</hi> and laſtly, this <hi>Curſed Popiſh Plot.</hi> Now, conſider according to the Law of Nations: If a Ship at Sea meeteth with another which ought to ſtrike to her, and ſhe refuſeth, then a warning Piece is ſent to her; if that make her not ſubmit, there is lot ſlie at her two or three Ordnance, if then ſhe will not do her duty, there is poured into her a Broadſide, which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly ſinketh her, and all that's in her. Even ſo, if no Judgment nor Warning will make us ſubmit in all things Spiritual to the Royal Scepter of the Lord Jeſus in his Church, to ſerve God in his Worſhip by the directions in his holy Teſtament, then may we expect unavoidably, that he will pour in on us Iris Murdering Places, the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who like the Armies of <note n="‖" place="margin">Rev. 20. 9</note> 
                  <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> compaſs the Tents of the Saints about, bringing great <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 21. 25.</note> diſtreſs of Nations, until Fire come down from Heaven, even at that day when the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from Heaven with his mighty Angels in flaming <note n="†" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 1. 8.</note> Fire, who ſhall reap the Harveſt of the Earth, in taking Vengeance on them that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall be deſtroyed from the glory of his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; when the Remnant of the Faithful, as in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> ſhall be preſerved, and caught up to meet the Lord in the Air, ſo ſhall they <note n="‖" place="margin">1 Theſſ. chap. 4.</note> ever be with the Lord.</p>
               <p>The ſum of all is, Seeing God hath ſaid, <hi>He will do nothing,</hi> (concerning Mercy or Judgment to his People) <hi>but he revealeth</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Amos 3. 7. Rom. 15. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>his Secrets to his Servants the Prophets;</hi> written in the holy Scriptures for all Chriſtians Admonition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which we have here laid before this preſent Age. The chief Cauſes why God brought his Judgments in Ages paſt were for Errors in Faith, and Corruptions in Worſhip. Seeing then there is but <note n="†" place="margin">Eph. 4. 5.</note> one Faith, and proper Object thereof, even the Evangelical Promiſe <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 1. 16.</note> of Grace in Chriſt, from the days of <hi>Adam,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the Faith of Jeſus</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 14. 12.</note>, <hi>once given to the Saints</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Jude 3.</note>, therefore called <hi>the Faith of God's Elect</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Tit. 1. 1.</note>; which Faith in God's Elect either more, or leſs, is built upon the <note n="*" place="margin">Epheſ 2. 20.</note> Foundation or Doctrine both of the Apoſtles and Prophets: So, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Article of any Chriſtian's Faith agreeth not to the Law and Teſtimony; that is, to the figures of Chriſt in the Law, the Schoolmaſter leading to Chriſt for fulfilling of the ſame in the New Teſtament, with applying the Promiſes to the right Subjects <note n="†" place="margin">Acts 2. 39.</note> they belong unto, with all the benefits thereof to be enjoyed in God's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is not the faith of God's Elect, but a falned Faith, which ſaveth not: So that whatſoever Faith is not thus proved (as it is written) <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Examine your ſelves,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>know ye not how that Chriſt is in you except ye be Reprobates?</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as Chriſt is ſaid to dwell <note n="†" place="margin">Epheſ. 3. 17.</note> in the heart by Faith, that is, by true belief: And hereupon it is written, <note n="*" place="margin">Mark 16. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>He that believeth not, ſhall be damned.</hi> How needful is it then that every ones Faith be right, ſeeing it is a matter that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns their Salvation.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:102616:18"/>
               <p>Secondly, As touching Worſhip; It hath been proved, that whatſoever Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, or Ordinance God is ſerved with, or by, after the Commandment and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Men, is <note n="*" place="margin">Col. 2. 22, 23.</note> Will-worſhip, which all are to periſh with the uſing: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the true Worſhip is to ſerve or worſhip God in <note n="†" place="margin">John 4. 24.</note> Spirit and in Truth; that is, by Faith in Chriſt, according to the word of Truth, as Chriſt the only Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver in Worſhip hath commanded.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, And for as much as God is a God of Order <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 40.</note>, therefore true Faith and Order in the performance of every Ordinance in the Worſhip of God, muſt go <note n="†" place="margin">Col. 2. 5.</note> together: Every Officer is to keep within the Order God hath placed him, and every Member within the bounds of their Places ſet in the <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 18.</note> Body. For the clear diſtinguiſhing of every Officer and Member's place and duty in Worſhip, as Members in the Body, ſee the Book fore-named, <hi>Ancient Truth Revived.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the breach of theſe things, God's Anger was ſtill kindled againſt his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; for which cauſe the Lord is now ſearching <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Zeph. 1. 12.</note> with Candles, and will puniſh the Luke-warm Carnal Profeſſors that are ſettled on their Lees, who make Worldly Gain and Pleaſure, their Religion and Godlineſs; <hi>Who ſay in their Hearts</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. 9. 9.</note>, <hi>either the Lord hath forſaken the Earth, or He will not do good, neither will he do evil.</hi> Thus as in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> is a ſtate of Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſeized on Profeſſors, ſaying, <hi>Soul, take thy eaſe:</hi> Let's build, plant, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Eat, Drink, joyn Houſe to Houſe, Field to Field, till there be no more place in the Earth: <hi>The Harp, the Viol, and Pipe</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Iſa. 5. 8, 12, 13.</note>, <hi>and Wine are in their Feaſts, but regard not the Works of the Lord, neither conſider the Operation of his Hands.</hi> Therefore on ſuch, both Famine and Captivity will come, ſo that <hi>their Goods ſhall become</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Zeph. 1. 13, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>a Booty, and their Houſes a Deſolation:</hi> Even as Chriſt hath ſaid; <hi>Diſtreſs</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Luke 21. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>of Nations, Mens hearts failing them for fear,</hi> and looking after thoſe things which (for the Sins aforeſaid) are coming on the Earth. The evident ſigns of the foregoing <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 24. 15, 21, 24.</note> Type of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>'s deſtruction, ſheweth that the time is near of Chriſt's coming to Judgment, true Faith ſo greatly decayeth among Men; as it is written, <hi>When the Son of Man cometh, ſhall he find</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Luk. 18. 8</note> 
                  <hi>Faith on Earth?</hi> Oh! that open <note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 27. 6</note> Rebuke may be in this Day better than ſecret Love, and the Wounds of a Friend better than the Kiſſes of an Enemy! And <hi>to give to any</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Job 32. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>flattering Titles I know not; for in ſo doing, my Maker will ſoon take me away:</hi> But have herein ſought the good of every Soul, yea the very <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 5. 44.</note> Enemies of all true Proteſtants, the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and deſire their Converſion, that the Lord upon their true Repentance may have mercy on them</p>
               <p>Now to conclude, by way of an healing Medicine both to the King's moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty, and all his good Subjects, in whom is the leaſt ſence and fear of the Judgments of God (for the Sins aforeſaid, or any other) ready to come on this Nation, that they would be pleaſed to remember that Word the Lord ſent to <hi>Judah,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 18. 7, 8, 9, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>At what inſtant I ſhall ſpeak concerning a Nation, and concerning a Kingdom, to pluck up, and to pull down, and to deſtroy it: If that Nation againſt whom I have pronounced, turn from their Evil, I will repent of the Evil that I thought to do unto them. And at what inſtant I ſhall ſpeak concerning a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and concerning a Kingdom, to build and to plant it: if it do evil in my ſight, that it obey not my Voice, then I will repent of the Good wherewith I ſaid I would benefit them.</hi> Therefore if all Degrees, both noble and ignoble, do believe, that it is not only for the Sins of ſome few in the Nation, (as Chriſt told the <hi>Jews</hi> of the <hi>Galileans,</hi> whoſe Blood <hi>Pilate</hi> had mingled with their Sacrifices: <note place="margin">Luke 13. 1, 2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Suppoſe ye,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>that theſe</hi> Galileans <hi>were Sinners above all the</hi> Galile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>becauſe they ſuffered theſe things? I tell you, nay; but except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh)</hi> but for the general Sins of all, ſome in one thing, and ſome in another, as afore noted. So that according to the Evil will the Puniſhment
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102616:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> be; as is ſhewed by the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> in the firſt and ſecond Chapters. The Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious are puniſhed for their Cruelty to the Lord's People; and the Religious People, both <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> were puniſhed, becauſe they had deſpiſed the Law of the Lord, and kept not his Commandments, which they <note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 19 8. Jer. 7. 23, 24.</note> promiſed to obey. Seeing then the Sin of Leproſy is ſpread over all Degrees, either in Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in Faith, and Diſorder in Worſhip, or Oppreſſion among Men, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all are ſhut up, as in a <note n="†" place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 15. 5.</note> ſevered Houſe, as unclean, becauſe by their Sins the Lord's Camp or Dwelling is <note n="‖" place="margin">Numb. 5. 2, 3.</note> defiled.</p>
               <p>Therefore, dear Proteſtants, under what other Title ſoever by Men called, Chriſt Jeſus, the great High-Prieſt, is <note n="*" place="margin">Levit 13. Heb. 4. 13.</note> looking on you. Therefore I ſhall cloſe up all to you with the Obſervation of that worthy Servant of the Lord, <hi>Henry Ainſworth,</hi> on <hi>Levit.</hi> 13. 15. who hath noted there, That it is one of the remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able things in the Law, <hi>That quick or ſound Fleſh in the Sore ſhould be judged Leproſy, and the Man pronounced unclean; whereas if the Leproſy cover all his Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh, he was pronounced clean.</hi> And hereby the Holy Ghoſt ſeems to teach, that if we would <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 31. 1 Joh. 1. 7.</note> judg our ſelves, we ſhould not be judged of the Lord, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 9. <hi>If we confeſs our Sins, he is faithful, and juſt to forgive us our Sins, and to cleanſe us from all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs.</hi> But if any quick or ſound Fleſh, that is, any <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 16. Eph. 2. 5. Rom. 11 6. Gal. 5. 4.</note> part of Health or Life be pretended in our ſinful Nature, or any whit of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs by Works of the Law, by which no Fleſh can be juſtified, then God pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth us unclean; for we cannot be juſtified but by the Faith of Jeſus. Therefore, with <hi>David,</hi> that we may find Mercy with the Lord, we muſt acknowledg, <hi>there is no ſoundneſs in our Fleſh, Pſal</hi> 38. 4, 8. Until this be done, God will leave us as unclean, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 15. 5. <hi>Numb.</hi> 12. 14. ſhut up from Deliverance from our Enemies, and Communion with himſelf, until we be humbled for our Sins, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1. 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. 1, 28. As it is written, <hi>Your Iniquities have ſeparated between you and your God, and your Sins have hid his Face from you, that he will not hear,</hi> Iſa. 59. 2.</p>
               <p>And laſtly; If in this <hi>Warning-piece</hi> I have unadviſedly, in zeal to God's Glory, and good Will and true Affections I bear to my Prince and Countrymen, let fall any words that do not become a Chriſtian, that is not warranted by God's Word, let the Righteous <note n="†" place="margin">Pſal. 146. 5.</note> ſmite me, and it ſhall be taken as a kindneſs. And let not any Proteſtant deſpiſe this plain way of diſcovering the Iniquities of theſe Times, becauſe it is not garniſhed with Eloquent Language; nor yet think with themſelves the Medicine is too ſharp to work a Cure at this time, but let all ſuch before they judg, or raſhly cenſure it, examine the Ingredients by that moſt Heavenly Herbal, God's written Word, and they ſhall find the whole Compoſition is gathered together by directions of God's Spirit in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants the Prophets and Apoſtles, all written for our Learning, gathered from the Tree of Life, whoſe Fruit is for Souls food, and the Leaves thereof for Healing of the Nations. Now if the Lord proſper it, is the thing deſired herein, and I have obtained my end, who am one of the Lord's unprofitable Servants, to bring any Glory to his Name, or Comfort to his People.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 9. lin. 2. <hi>Marg.</hi> for <hi>Mark</hi> read <hi>Mat.</hi> Pag. 19. lin. 15. for 113, 115. read 313, 315. P. 28. l. laſt, r. <hi>Alſo ſee</hi> Junius.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
